<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The plea of the children of believing-parents for their interest in Abraham's covenant, their right to church-member-ship with their parents, and consequently their title to baptism. The cause of publishing this discourse after so many learned men have laboured in this province, is declared in the preface to the reader. By Giles Firmin.</title>
            <author>Firmin, Giles, 1614-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 176 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41329</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F960</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216413</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828144</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828144</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32571</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41329)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32571)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1947:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The plea of the children of believing-parents for their interest in Abraham's covenant, their right to church-member-ship with their parents, and consequently their title to baptism. The cause of publishing this discourse after so many learned men have laboured in this province, is declared in the preface to the reader. By Giles Firmin.</title>
                  <author>Firmin, Giles, 1614-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 119, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Simons, at the Princes Arms in Ludgate-street, near Ludgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Dr. Williams's Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32571:1"/>
            <p>THE PLEA OF THE CHILDREN OF BELIEVING-PARENTS, <hi>for their Intereſt in</hi> Abraham<hi>'s Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, their Right to Church-Member-ſhip with their Parents, and conſequently their Title to BAPTISM.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Cauſe of publiſhing this Diſcourſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo many Learned Men have laboured in this Province, is declared in the <hi>Preface</hi> to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Baptizandos eſſe paruulos, nemo dubitet: quando nec illi hinc dubitant, qui ex parte aliqua Contradicunt. <hi>Auguſt,</hi> de verbis Apoſtoli.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Serm. 14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>It will ſurely be rewarded by Chriſt at the latter day, as a work of more then ordinary Charity, to have plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and maintained the Right of theſe poor Members of his, who want a Tongue to ſpeak for themſelves.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Tho. Goodwin,</hi> in his <hi>Preface</hi> to Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>GILES FIRMIN.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 7.14.</hi>
               </bibl>—Elſe were your Children <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean, but now they are Holy.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Simons,</hi> at the <hi>Princes Arms</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-Street,</hi> near <hi>Ludgate,</hi> 1683.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32571:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:32571:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32571:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IF the <hi>Reader</hi> demands a reaſon, why after ſo many Books written by other Men (far more able then my ſelf) upon this Subject, that now I ſhould appear? my anſwer is ready. I had as few thoughts of writing, as any Man could have of reading any thing of mine upon the Subject. But hearing of a Book againſt <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm,</hi> very much cryed up, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving ſome diſcourſe about <hi>Anabaptiſm</hi> this Spring, more in the Town then ever I heard before, I ſent to borrow the Book, I took a brief view of it, and the Book was ſent for again. To ſpend the <hi>Lord's-Day</hi> ſo much as one Exerciſe upon any Controverſie, I did
<pb facs="tcp:32571:4"/>much diſlike it, yet I thought I was bound to ſay ſomething to it, and did borrow a little time, before I went on my other courſe.</p>
            <p>About <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> We<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ks after I had done, come<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> down an <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aptiſt</hi> from <hi>London,</hi> to a Town Seven <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Miles diſtant from me, and writes me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Letter, informing me, <hi>That he was one that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d walk in Goſpel-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Col.</hi> Danvers, (<hi>ſometimes he ſtiles him Eſq</hi> Danvers) then writes to me thus. <hi>You have caſt the</hi> Odium <hi>of</hi> Falſhood <hi>and</hi> Fergery <hi>upon his Book to your</hi> Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory: <hi>If it was to deter your Hearers from reading his Book, it doth demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the badneſs of your Cauſe, in that you are not willing it ſhould be inſpected. If you deſign thereby to degrade the Gentleman, as infamous, though unknown, you have therein greatly erred,—there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I requeſt you on the behalf of Col.</hi> Danvers, <hi>that you be pleaſed to do him the common Juſtice, as to publiſh to the World in Print, what you have ſpoken in your more private Meetings, by way of detection of his</hi> Forgery,—<hi>and not only to Print what you have traduced him
<pb facs="tcp:32571:4"/>with, but alſo any other new things you have Preached, that will lend any aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to your</hi> Infant-Baptiſm, <hi>that this Gentleman doth endeavour to throw down as a ſpurious thing;—ſeveral of your own Party have written againſt him, but he, with others, have ſo anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, that they have ſet down ſilent under—The Collonel hath a better</hi> Character <hi>than you give of him,—he hath a large Portion of this Worlds goods, &amp;c.</hi> Thus he runs on in commendation of the Collonel, and ends it in ſuch a way, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I, nor others that read the Letter, could underſtand his meaning.</p>
            <p>As to this Letter, the <hi>Reader</hi> may pleaſe to underſtand, the Book which I borrowed had in the Title Page, only <hi>H.D.</hi> I could not tell whither <hi>D.</hi> ſtood <hi>for Den</hi> (whoſe name I had ſeen) or <hi>Dell,</hi> or <hi>Danvars,</hi> of whoſe name only I had heard, but never ſaw any thing of his; but whoever was the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> I found fault with him. <hi>1.</hi> For his <hi>Falſhood</hi> in the Hiſtorical part (which if my Memory fails me not, took up above half his Book.) <hi>2ly,</hi> His fraudulent dealing.
<pb facs="tcp:32571:5"/>
               <hi>3ly,</hi> His raiſing a duſt upon the Scriptures he quotes, to trouble his <hi>Reader. 4ly,</hi> For his <hi>Logick.</hi> But for any other Opinions, or any thing concerning his Converſation, I ſpeak not one word: for how could I, when I knew nothing of him, and only heard three times (as I remember) there was one Collonel <hi>Danvers,</hi> an <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> and that was all; nor was I certain the Book was his.</p>
            <p>It was never my intent to anſwer every particular in his Book, partly becauſe I would not ſpend the <hi>Lord's Day</hi> in Controverſies, and partly becauſe Catechizing was the thing I intended, being far more neceſſary, ſo that I did grudge the time I ſpent about this Book; out of which I only wrote the moſt material things, and the Book was ſent for away.</p>
            <p>For the new things, this <hi>Epiſtoler</hi> would have me publiſh. Doth he mean new Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, or new Arguments, or both?</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> Why new? ſince the old are not yet anſwered; it is one thing to write againſt Men, another to anſwer them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly,</hi> Why new? ſince my <hi>Author</hi> borrows ſo much old out of Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi>'s Book, which I look upon as <hi>inſtar omnium,</hi> and is the only <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> Book I have.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32571:5"/>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3ly,</hi> Why new? ſince my <hi>Author</hi> oppoſes old Texts, and I muſt take the part of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4ly,</hi> Why new? my <hi>Epiſtoler</hi> ſhould tell me what Controverſies are there, which have been handled ſo long, by very able Divines as this hath been, that he that comes laſt, hath wrote all new?</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5ly,</hi> To conclude then, as to theſe new things, I am forced to take up the old Texts, becauſe of my <hi>Author</hi>'s oppoſing them: I do but touch other Texts, and not inſiſt upon them, where others have been before me: for other Mens Arguments, I borrow but one from Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and tell you whoſe it is, and improve it my way. If I have hit upon other Mens notions, it is unknown to me, as I ſee I have upon Mr. <hi>Wills,</hi> in anſwer to the old <hi>Britains:</hi> but I had given the anſwer in the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and wrote it in my Coppy, before I ſaw Mr. <hi>Wills.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For his crying <hi>Victoria,</hi> telling me our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines <hi>ſit ſilent under the Anſwers the Collonel, and his Party have given them.</hi> If this <hi>Epiſtoler,</hi> read Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Second Defence of Infants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he may read a full
<pb facs="tcp:32571:6"/>anſwer to this, and the reaſon of their ſilence, <hi>p. 211.</hi> We may allow ſome Honour to a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel, but why do they ſit ſilent? not becauſe the Collonel, or any other <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> have put them to ſilence, by Arguments from Scripture, by Truth in Hiſtory, or Strength of Learning, the contrary appears to judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Readers:</hi> but who will care for dealing with unreaſonable Men? They have other work to do of higher concernment: Let the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> indulge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their Opinions and Practiſes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Redgneſſ.</hi> 24. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt,</hi> 1682.</note> if they pleaſe, I have performed that common Juſtice my <hi>Epiſtoler</hi> requires of me, only for brevities ſake, I left out ſeveral things I would have added; if this may do the Church of Chriſt any ſervice, I ſhall have my end, and bleſs God,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. FIRMIN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32571:6"/>
            <head>THE PLEA <hi>OF THE</hi> CHILDREN <hi>OF</hi> Beleiving-Parents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Right of the Children of Beleiving-Parents to Church-Memberſhip with their Parents, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to Baptiſm, was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ſtrongly oppoſed, nor better defended, than it hath been within theſe forty yearts in this <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation. I think there is enough Written to ſatisfie the minds of ſober Chriſtians; but the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the Church is not yet quiet, nor will be, till the Church Militant becomes Triumphant.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:32571:7"/>
            <p>A difference we may obſerve between Chriſtians now, and thoſe in former times in <hi>England,</hi> ſince I can remember: How wary were they then, what Doctrines they received: Tho' they would not pin their Faith upon any Mans Sleeve, yet they would conſider what Perſons they were for ſoundeſt of Faith, and Holineſs in Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, from whom they would receive any Doctrine, which hath made me wonder many times how this Doctrine of <hi>Anti-Pado Baptiſm,</hi> which was firſt hatch'd in the Brain of that Notorious <hi>Heretick</hi> [for ſo up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſearch I find him] <hi>Auxentius,</hi> Chereſhed by <hi>Pelagius,</hi> and afterwards revived by Men of corrupt Minds, and lewd Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; as that Learned and Pious <hi>Martyr,</hi> Mr. <hi>Philpot,</hi> tells his Fellow Priſoner in <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> That this wretched Doctrine as Mr. <hi>Thomas Hooker</hi> calls it, ſhould fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment in the Hearts of any truly Godly as it hath done in <hi>England</hi> of late: At this, as I ſaid, I have wondered! For this was not the frame of the Right Old <hi>Engliſh Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans,</hi> they would have abhorred the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine for the Authors ſake, Good Mr. <hi>Jeſſey,</hi> I knew between 50 and 60 years ſince, but then I heard of no Inclination this way: and one I have met with, truly Pious, ſound in all other Points humble, made
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32571:7"/>no noiſe of his Opinion, [whither <hi>Re-bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed,</hi> I cannot tell] with him we held Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in the <hi>Holy Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To me it ſeems ſtrange, and ſo ſtrange, that I will never believe it, That Chriſt ſhould Promiſe his Spirit to his Church, and that good Spirit ſhould ſuffer both his <hi>Martyrs</hi> and choice <hi>People</hi> to err in ſuch a Point [if it be an Error] from the Apoſtles days to this day. Since the Reformation, I believe <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> have, through Gods Rich Grace, afforded as many Holy, Heavenly, Gracious, and Learned Men, as any Nations under the Sun; As ſmart Enemies to <hi>Myſtical Babylon,</hi> [of which the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> tells us, Infant-Baptiſm is a Relique] as any <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> can be; and have done more againſt that <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> than all the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> that ever were or ſhall be, have done, or can do: and till of late years, I never heard of one [what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have done I know not] that did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, but did deteſt this Doctrine, till our unhappy Wars: in which time, and ſince that time, this Doctrine is much ſpread.</p>
            <p>May I have leave to inquire what ſhould occaſion the ſpreading of this Opinion in this Nation, [beſides the Soveraign plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God, who for wiſe ends, may ſuffer a Gracious Man to err in ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar]
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32571:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:32571:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:32571:9"/> I have thought of theſe Cauſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The firſt and chief Reaſon was, even good Men did not improve their <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-Abrahams-Covenant,</hi> nor their <hi>Infant-Baptiſm Covenant,</hi> as they ought. Hence not improving theſe, they did not experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the goodneſs of God in them, and our advantage by them; Then no wonder tho' Men in times of Diſpute and Temptations, be at a loſs, and come at laſt to deny that, which others, who have improved and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced, have found to be a greater privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, advantage, and ſupport to their Souls, under their fears, and other temptations.</p>
            <p>Experiences (you ſay) unleſs well ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Scriptures, are but deluding Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; I know it very well, therefore the grounds have been well weighed. On the other ſide, tho' the Scriptures be plain, yet the Goſpel, and things apprehended only by Faith, are ſuch, and Temptations about them [eſpecially in ſome Men] ſo ſtrong, that if a Man hath not attained to ſome experience of what he doth believe, if his Faith hath not brought in ſome Spiritual Senſe, in the <hi>Hurricanes</hi> of long and ſtrong Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, a Mans Faith will be terribly ſhaken in the very Goſpel it ſelf. The wind having blown at that Door before. I could not but take ſpecial notice of what the worthy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32571:9"/>of the Book, Intituled, <hi>The fulfilling of Scriptures,</hi> hath told us concerning that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Man, and Eminent Servant of Chriſt, Mr. <hi>Bruce,</hi> telling his People, <hi>I think it to be a greater matter to believe there is a God, than people judge,</hi> p. 430. The ſame Author ſpeaking about <hi>Experience</hi> [from his own <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience</hi> I doubt not] how it helps to Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that great Truth of <hi>Godhead,</hi> p. 111. in the next Page, 112. ſpeaks thus, <hi>It is not the Contemplation of Nature in its higheſt flight, can anſwer ſuch an Aſſault of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, which may try the moſt Eſtabliſhed Chriſtian Adult in the being of a God,</hi> &amp;c. but then he ſhews how <hi>Experience</hi> of God helps the Soul. Whether theſe be not Truths, I leave it to thoſe who have been long exerciſed with theſe Temptations; now if in that Point, as to the being of a God, than much more as to Goſpel Truths: that no wonder the Apoſtle Prays, <hi>that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leivers may abound in all Knowledge and Senſe,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 1 <hi>Phil.</hi> 9. we read <hi>Judgment,</hi> but the <hi>Greek</hi> word, and ſo the <hi>Margent</hi> tells you, is <hi>Senſe.</hi> The <hi>Arabick</hi> word is very ſignificant, <hi>Grotius</hi> and <hi>Gomarus,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by <hi>Senſe, Experience: Hemmingi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and <hi>Zanchie,</hi> opens the word excellently.</p>
            <p>Some Men are exerciſed with Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons exceedingly more than others, and God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32571:10"/>is pleaſed to be more Dark, or exceeding Dark to ſome over he is to others, which hath made me often think and ſay,</p>
            <p>It is only Divine Teaching, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimental <hi>Senſe</hi> of what is taught, that can make a ſound Chriſtian bear up and hold to the Word in the time of long and ſore Temptations. I could here give a very ſad but true Story, the like ſcarce ever heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, pertinent to the Point in hand; but I fear the Devil would make ill uſe of it among tempted Chriſtians, and therefore I will not commit it to Writing.</p>
            <p>To return to the Head I am upon. If the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſay, <hi>How can a Man improve a Nullity, and get Experience of it?</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams <hi>Covenant with the Seed of Believers, now is Null,</hi> Infant-Baptiſm <hi>is Null.</hi> True, I do not know how a Man can improve a <hi>Nullity.</hi> But I doubt not there are many <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> who lived ſeveral years before they drank in this Opinion of <hi>Anabaptiſm,</hi> and in that time did not think <hi>Abrahams Covenant,</hi> nor their <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> to be Null; many of them alſo had Parents not only viſible, but real Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; I appeal to their Conſciences, did you in that time before you drank in this Opinion, improve the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and your <hi>Infant-Baptiſm?</hi> did you mind theſe? did
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32571:10"/>you meditate well upon them? did you believe them upon theſe Meditations and Faith? did you follow God cloſe and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Prayer for the benefits of them? and tho' you met with Temptations, yet did you hold on? and what, did God give you in nothing, no ſupport, no relief, no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from theſe? did you find no advantage to your Souls by theſe? I will never believe it. God is gracious, God is faithful, what ever we think of him in our dark hours I will rather believe they did not follow cloſe their improvement of theſe, for I meet but with very few, even good Chriſtians, tho' they hate <hi>Anabaptiſm,</hi> that do improve them as they ought. No wonder then tho' Men cry out, <hi>Abrahams Covenant is Null,</hi> and <hi>Infant-Baptiſm Null,</hi> when they never improved them, ſo found no good by them, and now turn <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know Chriſtians that lie under ſome Temptations, may, and do expect more from the <hi>Covenant,</hi> Promiſe, and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, than God intended, or the Scripture holds forth, they would make one Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture contradict another: If God gives in but a little, and will ſuffer us to lie under our Temptations, but yet will ſupply us with ſo much from his <hi>Covenant,</hi> that we are able to hold up our hands in the day of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32571:11"/>Battel: that our Hearts are kept cloſe to him, and do not in the leaſt depart from him; If we cannot get the fatted Calf, and Muſick, <hi>&amp;c. Luke</hi> 15.23. [which ſome Chriſtians have] if we can but get a Kid, and have a Father to own us at laſt, 'tis worth our Beleiving, Praying, and Writing.</p>
            <p>What it was that Woman [a noted Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife I knew] expected to find at the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> I know not, but it ſeems ſhe found it not: whereupon ſhe forſooke the <hi>Lords Table,</hi> with this blaſphemous Speech, <hi>A Man may find as much good by a Loaf in the Bakers Shop, as by the Bread in the Lords Supper, for ſhe had been often there and could find no good.</hi> Hearing of this Speech, I inquired after her, by thoſe who had been long acquainted with her [I know not whether I ſaw her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I heard it] they took her alwaies for a civil Woman, but did not think ſhe was acquainted with the work of Regeneration; but that made me to wonder the more, for ſuch perſons commonly take up their Prieſt in the work done, in above partaking of the Ordinance.</p>
            <p>If Chriſtians be at this Point, we expect ſo much from Promiſes, ſo much from Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, or we have nothing, then we may do as ſhe did, throw off all Ordinances, and Promiſes too. Tho' I am far from attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32571:11"/>what I have ſought and deſired, yet I bleſs God, ſo much I have attained from my underſtanding, and improving of <hi>Abrahams Covenant,</hi> and my <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> that I have but a light eſteem of all the <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> Books againſt them, they ſignifie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing with me: but of this, more hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Diſputing without experiencing, ſignifies little in Divinity to a tempted Soul. But this I doubt not to affirm, Did Chriſtians ſet in earneſt to their work, and labour to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove <hi>Abrahams Covenant,</hi> and their <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> they ſhould find as much profit, advantage, and ſupport to their Souls, as any <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> do by their <hi>Dipping</hi> when Adult. But if Ordinances be not improved, how can Men expect any good by them?</p>
            <p>When God made that <hi>Covenant</hi> with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> to be the God of him and his Seed, and appointed the ſeal of his <hi>Covenant</hi> to be Adminiſtred to the <hi>Infant</hi> on the eigth day. Might not? ought not <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Jews,</hi> and did not many of them when they came to years of diſcretion, and were taught the meaning of them, improve them to their Souls advantage? why then may not we as well improve the ſame <hi>Covenant,</hi> and our <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> when we are come to years of diſcretion, to our Spititual advantage,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32571:12"/>when we underſtand them by our Paſtors and Parents teaching?</p>
            <p>If there be ſuch an advantage in <hi>Adult-Baptiſm,</hi> over there is in <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> what is the matter that ſome of them could ſay, they found no ſuch good by it? and I do believe them by their Converſation; but eſpecially, what is the reaſon that ſo many hundreds of them caſt off both <hi>Infant</hi> and <hi>Adult-Baptiſm,</hi> and deny <hi>Baptiſm</hi> alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, for which they were ſometime ſo zealous? if there had been ſuch advantage in it, they would not have done ſo wickedly to caſt away ſuch an Inſtitution of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> A ſecond thing which might occaſion this, is, That ſo many Children of Godly Parents, who were Dedicated to God in <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in their Infancy, and Parents have beſtowed great pains in their Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet prove wicked.</p>
            <p>The deeper the wounds of ſuch Parents, and the ſorer the damnation of ſuch Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren without Repentance.</p>
            <p>But firſt, We may obſerve the greateſt number of viſible, yea true Chriſtians in the viſible Church, conſiſt of the Children of ſuch Parents.</p>
            <p>Since the Flood of Iniquity of late years brake in upon this Nation, it hath riſen ſo high that it hath flown into the Houſes of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32571:12"/>Godly Parents, more than ever it did ſince <hi>England</hi> knew the Goſpel. This is a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Was it not ſo in <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s Family, where but two, and one naught.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thridly,</hi> We never underſtood that when God made that <hi>Covenant</hi> with our <hi>Father Abraham,</hi> and his Seed, that he intended to make all his Seed Godly; but we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſuch a Priviledge in it, that neither Parents nor Children, who have their Eyes opened, will part with it, let the <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> write what they pleaſe againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> But do this <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>None deny that Regenerate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, <hi>he muſt ſay only, elſe he oppoſed not us Chriſtins Scrip. pract. of Int.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 147, 148.</note> and <hi>Re-Baptiſing</hi> of Adult perſons help it? are they all Godly? If the Elect and Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate be the only Subjects of <hi>Babtiſm,</hi> [as my Author tells me] I am ſure they are not of <hi>Anabaptiſm,</hi> to my knowledge, unleſs drunkenneſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, be Notes of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; we ſhall not need to go to <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> to inquire, <hi>England</hi> will afford proof enough. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath given us a ſad account of ſome of them, enough to make a ſerious Chriſtian afraid of the Opinion. By a ſerious Chriſtian who came from <hi>New-England,</hi> we are informed, That a [<hi>Sea-man</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:32571:13"/>as I remember] one being Baptiſed, how long the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> held him under Water I know not, but ſo ſoon as his Head was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Water, he wrapt out an Oath [ſo I heard it] <hi>what do you make account to drown me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Another is this, The great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary of Chriſt and his Church, ſeeing how earneſtly the Spirits of good Chriſtians were ſet for the Reformation of the Church in all Points, according to the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which we profeſs, to hinder this work, by dividing of Chriſtians, and raiſing Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities one againſt another, uſed this for one Engine. Baptiſing of Infants of Belei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Parents, being the Opinion and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of ſuch Chriſtians, they muſt now be thrown by, becauſe in the Scriptures we can no where read that Chriſt gave command to his Apoſtles to Baptiſe Infants. While I was anſwering this Book, word was ſent me, That there was one who would Diſpute with me in the Congregation, expecting his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and knowing he had thrown away <hi>Water-Baptiſm;</hi> for an Introduction to my work, I laid down Ten Arguments to prove that <hi>Water-Baptiſm</hi> was ſtill an Inſtitution of Chriſt, obliging all that profeſſed Faith in him, to practiſe, to hear what he would ſay to them, judging it a ſilly act in him, to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32571:13"/>come to oppoſe me in <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> who had renounced <hi>Water-Baptiſm</hi> altogether: but that day which he ſaid he would come, he did not. About three Weeks after he did, and this was all he had againſt me [what concerned others I regard not] <hi>Where did Chriſt give command to Baptiſe Infants?</hi> To this I had ſpoken ſeveral times before, that this was no New thing to the Congregation. There was no ſuch expreſs command in thoſe words I granted, but there was a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to Baptiſe Infants, implyed, included in that command of Chriſt to his Apoſtles, to Baptiſe Diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. I framed my Argument, but the Man could not tell which Propoſition to deny: but after ſome words [little to the purpoſe] civilly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted.</p>
            <p>They who deſire the Reformation of the Church, do not ſay every thing muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſet down in Scripture; but if it be contained in the Scripture, and by neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſequence deducted from thence, we are bound to believe, or practiſe it.</p>
            <p>Our Lord taught us this in proving the Reſurrection againſt the <hi>Sadduces;</hi> A Point of infinite more conſequence, then the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing of an Infant. For if there be no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, to what purpoſe is our Religion? But according to the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> Argument,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32571:14"/>that Call for an expreſs command to baptiſe Infants, and therefore reject it, our Lord did not prove the Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>I will perſonate a <hi>Sadduce,</hi> and take their Argument; the Queſtion is, <hi>Shall there be a Reſurrection of the Dead?</hi> The <hi>Sadduce</hi> denies it, our Lord affirms it, and proves it from <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.6. <hi>I am the God of Abraham,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.29.31. <hi>v.</hi> But what is this to the proof of the Queſtion, <hi>Doth God ſay expreſly to Moſes, there ſhall be a Reſurrection of the Dead?</hi> if ſo, then we will <hi>believe</hi> it, elſe not. Thus the <hi>Anabaptiſt, Doth Chriſt expreſly command the Apoſtles to Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiſe Infants?</hi> then we will <hi>Practiſe</hi> it, elſe we Condemn it. But tho' God did not expreſly ſay there ſhall be a Reſurrection, yet he ſaid that, which by neceſſary Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence will force it. For tho' <hi>Jacob,</hi> who died laſt of the three, had been dead two hundred years, when God ſpake thoſe words, yet he ſaith, he is their God, <hi>but he is not the God of the dead, but of the living;</hi> Mark 12.28. The people ſaid, <hi>He anſwer'd them well,</hi> and 22 Matth. 33. <hi>They were astoniſhed at it.</hi> Yet I may ſay, the neceſſity of this Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, from that Antecedent, is nothing ſo obvious and clear to many, even good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as the Conſequence of Infants of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving-Parents, being under <hi>Abrahams Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:32571:14"/>and Church-Members with their Parents. But what miſchief this Principle and Practice hath done, and how it hath ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Devils Deſign, we are ſad Witneſſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Tho' I do not put ſo much ſtreſs upon this, becauſe the Argument of the <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> caſt out all the Poſterity of the ſoundeſt Believers, and holy Men, as well as the moſt wicked out of the Church; yet I believe this hath helped on with the reſt, to ſee what ignorant and debauched perſons [becauſe it is the Mode of the Nation] re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire Baptiſm for their Children, and it is Adminiſtred to them. The <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> Principle is, <hi>That Regenerate Perſons are the only Subject of Baptiſm,</hi> but how far is this Practice from their Principle? This doth a little confirm me in it; becauſe that Man whom I mentioned in my firſt <hi>Page,</hi> with whom we held Communion; when thoſe who are eſteemed godly, and he did think ſo, had Children to be baptized, he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red he might know it, and would be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the Adminiſtration, though he was not clear for <hi>Infant-Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I will ſay, I had rather baptize the Children of ſome <hi>Heathen,</hi> than of many who are called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> their <hi>Ignorance</hi> is not more, nor <hi>Converſations</hi> worſe, and yet theſe <hi>Chriſtians</hi> have lived long under Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-light:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32571:15"/>Had they but the knowledge required in the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> in the <hi>Common-Prayer-book,</hi> and Converſations as civil as ſome <hi>Indians</hi> I have known, it were tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; but when men are asked,</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> A good old man.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> A courteous young Gentleman.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How many Gods are there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Ten.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How many Commandments are there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Two.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Salvation.</p>
            <p>What the ſecond was he forgot that ſtood by, and ſhewed the three laſt Queſtions, [the firſt two were another perſon's] and profeſſed to my Father-in-law, when he came to have his Child baptized, That he anſwered him as well as he could. For want of Catechiſing and good Diſcipline in Church and State: Into what a miſerable condition is this Nation fallen? That this hath helped on among theſe who are godly <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> I do not much doubt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> I cannot exclude the holy and juſt government of God. When people come to be glutted with the precious Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-truths, the life of a Chriſtian; theſe are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32571:15"/>ſtale and common; <hi>new things</hi> would be welcome. I doubt not to ſay, God may permit ſome of his own dear people to fall into ſome Errour, which in them he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looks and pardons: when others ſhall take up that Errour, and bear up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in it, becauſe ſuch godly men were of that Opinion, and that Errour to them, ſhall be an inlet to other Errours, and ſo fall from one to another, filling their heads with notions, and ſpending time in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute about ſlight matters, and ruine their Souls at laſt. I thought it was a ſmart and terrible ſpeech of <hi>Tertullian, Nec periclitor dicere,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Nor do I think it any danger to ſay, The very Scriptures themſelves to be ſo ordered or diſpoſed by the will of God, that they ſhould miniſter matter to Hereticks, when I read there muſt be Hereſie,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.19. <hi>which without the Scriptures could not be.</hi> De pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrip. adv. Haeret. p. 86.</p>
            <p>And here I cannot but obſerve the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God [I can call it no other] That two great Corporations I know, where there were great Aſſemblies of <hi>Anaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſts,</hi> [It is the ſame in many other places in <hi>England</hi>] the greateſt number of them turned <hi>Quakers,</hi> the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> Society dwindle almoſt to nothing. Thus they who threw off <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> throw off
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32571:16"/>the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> it ſelf, <hi>the Lord's Supper,</hi> and the great Goſpel-truth, ſetting up <hi>Self,</hi> and <hi>a Heatheniſh morality,</hi> being now fallen into the <hi>Mare mortuum,</hi> from which few or none return.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Another thing which hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed to draw away ſome honeſt meaning perſons, not able to judge, have been, the great ſtreſs and abſolute neceſſity the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> put upon <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and <hi>their Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> for ſo they ſtyle themſelves <hi>the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized Congregations,</hi> and none baptized but themſelves, which ſtrikes divers good Chriſtians with fear; and what great good things they may expect who do come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their way, being Rebaptized, from <hi>Mark</hi> 16. This Text <hi>Peter de Bruis</hi> a <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſian</hi> [in great eſteem with my Author, for his judgment againſt <hi>Infant-Baptiſm;</hi> though herein, as in other things charged upon him, by his railing <hi>Popiſh Adverſary,</hi> who took them up by Report from others, he confeſſeth, it is thought he is abuſed,] makes great uſe of,
<note place="margin">neutrum enim ſine alteo ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat.</note> and tells us, <hi>Not one of theſe alone doth ſave, but joyntly; not Baptiſm without our own proper Faith; nor our own proper Faith without Baptiſm, is able to do any thing; neither of them without the other ſaveth. Therefore though Infants
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32571:16"/>be baptized by you, yet becauſe by the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance of their, they cannot believe, by no means are they ſaved.</hi> With other ſtrange Tenets, not worthy the Tranſcribing. If my Author be not of the ſame Opinion with this <hi>De Bran,</hi> [if he be not abuſed] why doth he ſo much glory of him in his Book, and in his <hi>Title-page?</hi> And if this be true, <hi>That ſound Faith in Chriſt cannot ſave without perſons be of age, and Dowzed over Head and Ears;</hi> no wonder though they who believe it, yield to <hi>Dipping.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I intend not to meddle with the <hi>Opinion,</hi> only this I ſay, <hi>They who do believe Jeſus Chriſt to be God-man in one Perſon truly Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel, do reverence the Inſtitution of Chriſt, and do acknowledge a neceſſity of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> both a <hi>Neceſſitas modii &amp; praecepti,</hi> nor dare we omit it: Yea, ſome of the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians,</hi> [which I note becauſe of the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quers,</hi> ſome of which I know to be rather worſe than <hi>Socinians,</hi> as to the Perſon of Chriſt, and deny <hi>Baptiſm</hi> altogether; as alſo the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> and no wonder] do acknowledge <hi>Baptiſm</hi> not to be a thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, but neceſſary, as <hi>Martin. Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chonicius,</hi> and a <hi>means of Salvation,</hi> as <hi>Schlichtingius, That no man is to be eſteemed a Member of the Church of Chriſt without Baptiſm,</hi> as <hi>Oſtorodus.</hi> Therefore he thinks,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32571:17"/>and <hi>Socinus,
<note place="margin">Socin. Proflig. de Baptiſ.</note> That Infants may be baptized.</hi> All quoted with the Pages of their Books, by <hi>Calonius;</hi> and tells us alſo, <hi>That in a Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Synod,</hi> held <hi>Anno</hi> 1636. in <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> [as I underſtand it was] the <hi>Synod</hi> conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for <hi>Water-bapiſm, In the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</hi> So that the <hi>Quaker</hi> as to <hi>Goſpel Ordinances,</hi> and other greateſt <hi>Goſpel-truths,</hi> are the worſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Chriſt hath among them who own the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which they do after a faſhion.</p>
            <p>But though we own the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Baptiſm,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The neceſſity of Baptiſm, both for the</hi> Adult <hi>and</hi> little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <hi>but not</hi> abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſity.</note> yet we do not think a ſound Believer in Chriſt dying without <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> ſhall be damned: Our Lord doth not ſay in the next words <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>but he that belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not, nor is baptized, ſhall be damned.</hi> Sound Believers may be hindred from <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm,</hi> and have been ſo.</p>
            <p>How the Hopes of <hi>ſpiritual advantage,</hi> as to more <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>ſenſe of God's Love.</hi> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Suaſions</hi> ſome <hi>Sectaries</hi> have uſed to draw honeſt perſons into their way, have prevailed, and how miſerably they have complained after of <hi>Diſappointment,</hi> I could give Inſtance.</p>
            <p>The Learned <hi>Reignolds Praeter.</hi> 3. <hi>de Lib.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:32571:17"/>Apoc.</hi> doth aſſert, with many others whom he mentions.</p>
            <p>I can alſo inſtance one Woman reputed for a ſerious Chriſtian, who hearing an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſt,</hi> and after diſcourſing with him, he told her, ſhe muſt unravel all again, ſhe wanted this Ordinance of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> put her into ſuch a fright, that the Woman could not be quiet in her mind till ſhe was Dipped, and then fell diſtracted, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver recovered. I had this from her own re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> drive the <hi>Indians</hi> to Baptiſm; and the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> ſcar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſound Chriſtians, baptized to <hi>Anabaptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wrote to an Acquaintance of mine in a Corporation where were many <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> to certifie me about the Converſation of <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi> He anſwers me, they are moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered away to nothing, moſt turn <hi>Quakers.</hi> Two that lived the next door to him were the beſt he knew. The Woman, when <hi>Dipt,</hi> thought ſhe was in a ſtate of Salvation, [as ſhe ſaid] but threw off that all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Prayer. He a little before his Death, ſlighted the Blood of Chriſt, and both died <hi>Quakers;</hi> yet by their carriage drew divers to be <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:32571:18"/>
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p>As to the Book it ſelf, who ever was the Author, I charged it with falſhood in the Hiſtorical part: When I ſent to borrow it again, a ſecond Edition was ſent me, then I ſaw the Letter was true, which aſſured me Colonel <hi>Danvers</hi> was the Author; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of Authors more added than were in the firſt: A whole Regiment is drawn up, to the admiration of the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> that now cry <hi>Victoria,</hi> if he doth not abuſe his Authors, and the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> too, which he hath moſt groſly.</p>
               <p>For the ancient Fathers, ſeveral of them I had read, and knew them to be contrary to his Opinion: But to follow Authors in particular, I thought it a vain thing on the <hi>Lords-Day,</hi> and that in a Country Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. His quoting of the old <hi>Britains,</hi> and the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> as being Enemies to <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm,</hi> I took notice of, anſwered that and no more. Of which a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards.</p>
               <p>As to the numerous company of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors he hath quoted, I ſhall ſay but two things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> I deſire my Author to tell us if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them all he can find, who was the Author of <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> if it be an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour; as we can tell him who firſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32571:18"/>
                  <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> Hereticks not of the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er rank.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Lord Brooks,</hi> is a perſon whom the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> would perſwade us, was one of their <hi>Sect,</hi> becauſe of ſome Lines of his, with which I accord: But he tells us what prevailed with him on the contrary; his words are theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For ought I could ever learn, it was the conſtant cuſtom of the pureſt and moſt primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church,</hi> [mark Sir, not myſtical <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> then] <hi>to baptize the Infants of believing Parents: For I could never find the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and firſt Riſe of this Practice; where as it is very eaſie to tract Hereſies to their firſt riſing up and ſeting foot in the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This agrees with what I am upon, why then do you quote him as if he were <hi>yours?</hi> As for what he ſaith about <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> Sir, you are the <hi>Schiſmatick,</hi> for I have kept Communion with a godly <hi>Anabaptiſt;</hi> but one tells me, that he deſired Communion with one of your Churches, but they would not admit him to Communion, becauſe he would not be dipped.</p>
               <p>I ſee my Author hath named Maſter <hi>D. Rogers,</hi> as if he did favour his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, when as living in the next Town to him, and having intimate acquaintance with him, I knew him to be a ſmart Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to the <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:32571:19"/>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing I would ſay to them, is this, That ancient Father, pious, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and learned <hi>Auſtin</hi> flouriſhed above twelve hundred years before my Author, or any <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> in <hi>England</hi> was born; then he lived ſo many years nearer the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Churches, than my Author, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our <hi>Anabaptiſts:</hi> Whether then <hi>B. Auſtin,</hi> or thoſe <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſhould beſt know the practice of the Primitive Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches as to Baptizing of Infants, let a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſober man judge: He being a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo learned and ſo famous, no queſtion had all thoſe Authors which my Author quotes, that wrote before him, if not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more which we have not: And did not that learned pious Father underſtand them as well as my Author, or any <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> now in <hi>England?</hi> And though he was no Chriſtian himſelf, yet was not he acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the practice of the <hi>Greek Churches</hi> in his time better than our <hi>Anabaptiſts?</hi> Now he ſaith, the practice of <hi>Infant-baptiſm</hi> was ſo univerſal in the Church,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auſtin.</hi> l. 1. <hi>de peccat. mer. &amp; reniſ. c.</hi> 26. <hi>De baptiſ. contra. Denat.</hi> l. 2. c. 7. &amp; l. 4. c. 24.</note> that it could not but come from the Apoſtles. <hi>Eccleſia ſemper habuit, &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> ever heard it, ſaith he.</p>
               <p>Had not <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpoke true, there was one did watch him <hi>[Pelagius]</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:32571:19"/>who would have told him of it to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, for that Practice ſtood in <hi>Pelagius</hi>'s way, but <hi>Pelagius</hi> did not deny it.</p>
               <p>And whereas my Author doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the Writers as to this Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, that wrote after the Third <hi>Centuary;</hi> I am very confident there is no Author that wrote in the three firſt <hi>Centuaries,</hi> that have any thing in them to oppoſe the bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of the Infants of believing Parents; but on the contrary, ſome of them ſpeak for it.</p>
               <p>They that read the moſt ancient Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters next the Apoſtles, may ſee the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject matter they treated upon, did not give them any occaſion to ſpeak of <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> they had other Points in hand.</p>
               <p>As to the old <hi>Britains,</hi> I was a little ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to read them brought againſt <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> the Proof my Author brings out of <hi>Fabianus,</hi> I did read in him, but I much queſtion the truth of <hi>Fabianus,</hi> becauſe Mr. <hi>Fox,</hi> giving us an account what <hi>Auſtin</hi> the Monk required of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Biſhops when he came into <hi>England;</hi> tells us, <q rend="margQuotes">He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired that they ſhould Preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel to the <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> and that they ſhould among themſelves reform certain Rites and uſages in their Church, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for keeping <hi>Eaſtertide,</hi> and Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing after the manner of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:32571:20"/>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> quotes ſeveral Authors beſides <hi>Fabianus,</hi> for this: But that paſſage, <hi>That they ſhould give Chriſtendom to children,</hi> which <hi>Fabianus</hi> reports, he doth not mention.</p>
               <p>To Baptize after the manner of <hi>Rome,</hi> to uſe their Ceremonies in Baptiſm, and to baptize Children; differ much. I ſearched what Ceremonies were then uſed in <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Gregory</hi>'s time, and no wonder though the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Biſhops rejected them.</p>
               <p>But that the old <hi>Britains</hi> were againſt <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm,</hi> is very falſe, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> I thus prove.</p>
               <p>What year God firſt ſent the Goſpel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England,</hi> the Learned do not agree; there ſeem to be ſtrong grounds to believe, that it was before King <hi>Lucius</hi> ſent to <hi>Eleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therius</hi> B. of <hi>Rome;</hi> ſome ſay it was, <hi>An.</hi> 156, others 169, others 170, others 180. The Conteſt between <hi>Auſtin</hi> and <hi>Pelagius,</hi> was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 417, in the 63 year of <hi>Auſtins</hi> life, as <hi>Bucolcerus</hi> gathers. <hi>Pelagius</hi> denied Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sin; upon that denied Infant-Baptiſm as being ſuperfluous: not becauſe Infants cannot believe, which is the ſole Argument of our <hi>Anabaptiſts, Pelagius</hi> a learned man would have ſlighted ſuch an Argument as this. <hi>Auſtin</hi> proves Infants to be guilty of Original Sin, from the univerſal practice of the Church to take away Original Sin, they did baptize Infants: Now this Infant-baptiſm
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32571:20"/>ſaith <hi>Auſtin, The Church ever had it, ever held it,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>De verb. Apo. Ser.</hi> 10.</note> they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this from the faith of their Anceſtors, and this will it keep with perſeverance to the end.</hi> Let <hi>Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> who was a <hi>Britain,</hi> anſwer this: <hi>Brita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> had received the Goſpel 240 years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Conteſt. <hi>Pelagius</hi> knew the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of his own Country, and if it had been true, that the old <hi>Britains</hi> did not bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize Infants, as my Author ſaith, why did not <hi>Pelagius</hi> Confute <hi>Auſtin,</hi> charge him with falſhood; the <hi>Britains</hi> do not baptize Infants, <hi>ergo,</hi> it is not the practice of the Univerſal Church: This being an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Auſtin</hi> did ſo urge, and put ſo much ſtreſs upon it, <hi>Pelagius</hi> would have remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it if he could.</p>
               <p>But ſo far was <hi>Pelagius</hi> and his followers from denying what <hi>Auſtin</hi> affirmed, that <hi>Celeſtius</hi> a <hi>Pelagian,</hi> in a Book which he put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orth at <hi>Rome,</hi> hath theſe words, which <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> quotes out of it; <hi>We do confeſs that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants ought to be baptized for remiſſion of ſins, according to the rule of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church, and according to the ſentence of the Goſpel,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hough <hi>Caeleſtius</hi> do not mention the Text, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et by the following words, we may plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſee he means, <hi>John</hi> 3.5. <hi>Except a man be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orn again of Water and of the Spirit.</hi> So that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:32571:21"/>according to this <hi>Pelagian,</hi> here is <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ground,</hi> and the <hi>Rule of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church for Infant-Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then for the old <hi>Britains,</hi> they were not againſt <hi>Infant-baptiſm:</hi> Now then for the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> were I to charge any Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or practice upon other Churches, I ſhould firſt look to the Confeſſion of their Faith, then I may boldly charge them or not. As we have a few Anabaptiſtical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in <hi>England,</hi> ſhould their Books a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years hence fall into the hands of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts in foreign parts, ſhould they then aſſirm that the Church of <hi>England,</hi> [or the Churches in <hi>England</hi>] were <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts,</hi> would not this be falſe, and take it as a wrong done unto us? View the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> of the Aſſembly of Divines, of the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents in <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>New England,</hi> all their Confeſſions declare for <hi>Infant-baptiſm.</hi> Thus ſhould my Author have done, if he would deal honeſtly with the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> produce their Confeſſion of Faith, and the Article in which they condemn <hi>Infant-bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</hi> In the Articles which I have read o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, I find no ſuch thing, but that <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm ought to be Adminiſtred only with pure Water, without any mixture of hallowed Oyl.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:32571:21"/>
               <p>The Miniſters in the <hi>Vallies of Piemont,</hi> in the year 1532, when the Anabaptiſts in <hi>Germany</hi> were riſen up, in the 17th Article of their Confeſſion, declare for Infant-bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm: The Churches in thoſe Vallies, kept chaſte to Chriſt from the Apoſtles times, and were long before the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> were named; they were called <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> but this was a Nick-name put upon them by their Adverſaries, to make the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that their Religion was but a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty. [<hi>Morland. p.</hi> 12.]</p>
               <p>In the Confeſſion of the Faith of the <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes</hi> in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> (ſo <hi>Vergerius</hi> three times calls them) the 12th Article Declares for Infant-baptiſm, <hi>Anno</hi> 1535. As the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts roſe up, ſo the Churches drew up their Confeſſions againſt them: The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in their Preface to their Confeſſion, write, <q rend="margQuotes">That ſome malicious Spirits, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would caſt all the <hi>Odium</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them that they could, did reckon them amongſt the Anabaptiſts. But they anſwer, <hi>Nos ex factione Anabaptiſtarum non eſſe, nemini ignotum eſt.</hi> All men know they were none of that <hi>Faction,</hi> nor had any thing to do with the Anabaptiſts. The Doctrine they confeſſed in their Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, they held and owned, before the name of the Anabaptiſts was ſo much as heard of.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:32571:22"/>
               <p>So that my Author hath plainly abuſed both the old <hi>Britains,</hi> and the <hi>Waldenſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obſerving how my Author and Mrs. <hi>Tombs</hi> inſulted over Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and he that gave me the Challenge to Print, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling me, <hi>All my Party were ſilent,</hi> and I li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in a Country ſmall Town, and not hearing what Books came forth, I could not tell what to think of it; but when I wrote my Copy for the Preſs, I left here a ſpace, till I wrote to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> to know whether he had met with any Arguments to change his thought. I thank him, he ſent me down his Book in anſwer to them both. Then one lent me Mr. <hi>Wills.</hi> I heard alſo of Mr. <hi>Whitſton,</hi> but I ſaw none of theſe Authors till my Copy was written, but I ſee they have anſwered Mr. <hi>Danvers</hi> to purpoſe, diſcovered his groſs falſhood and forgery. Another Divine I met with that knows Mr. <hi>Danvers,</hi> though he hath not written againſt him, yet he hath ſo traced him, that he told me, never did <hi>Jeſuites</hi> abuſe Authors in their <hi>Quotations,</hi> more than he hath done.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> practice lies this way, we may ſee in <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who quotes <hi>Ten</hi> of the Fathers to juſtifie his Doctrine of <hi>Chriſts preaching to the Spirits in priſon,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.19. when as <hi>Six</hi> of them (I may
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:32571:22"/>ſay, <hi>Eight</hi> of them) give that Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Text, which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf condemns. See (ſaith that pious and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Reignolds) With what Conſcience theſe Jeſuites handle the Controverſies of Religion;</hi> which may well be applyed to Mr. <hi>Danvers,</hi> abuſing ſo many Authors as he hath done. [<hi>Reignold. Praelec.</hi> 86. <hi>de lib. Apochr. p.</hi> 1044. <hi>See him again, p.</hi> 1083.]</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECTION III.</head>
               <p>Leaving then the Hiſtorieal part, by which Infant-baptiſm is much confirmed: Let us come to the holy Scriptures, out of which our Divines who have laboured in this Controverſie, have produced ſo many, that I know not how more can be well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; where therefore others have been large, I will be brief.</p>
               <p>One man I knew (though I had no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward acquaintance with him) about fifty years ſince, a Mechanick, and Head of a ſeparate Company in thoſe days; he had none but his <hi>Mother-tongue,</hi> but a very good head in <hi>Polemical Divinity.</hi> This Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Anti-paedobaptiſm</hi> then being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to him, he rejected, though he had other Arguments againſt it, yet I took notice of this: <hi>I obſerve</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ever ſince God had a people upon the earth, he made a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:32571:23"/>difference between the families of his ſervants, and of wicked men, even before the flood,</hi> Gen. 6.2. There is not only <hi>truth,</hi> but <hi>ſtrength</hi> in it, what-ever the Anabaptiſts ſcribble againſt it.</p>
               <p>Two Texts eſpecially my Author pitch upon, becauſe he thinks we build much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. &amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. and ſo we do: theſe he labours to take from us. That the children of the <hi>Jews</hi> were Church-members with their Parents, the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts acknowledge: Then they were made ſo, by this Covenant of God with <hi>Abraham</hi> and with his Seed, and the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Circumciſe them; here then we muſt begin.</p>
               <p>From the 17. <hi>Gen.</hi> 7. I lay the Argument thus.</p>
               <p>A gracious Covenant made, ſigned, and ſealed by God, with a believing Perſon and his Seed, and never repealed by God; that Covenant remaineth in force, and is to be ſigned and ſealed unto his Seed.</p>
               <p>But that Covenant of God with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> (to be his God, and the God of his Seed, was ſuch a Covenant, and never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, <hi>Therefore</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This we premiſe, There is a great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the outward Adminiſtration of an Ordinance, and the inward Effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? This is clear in the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:32571:23"/>preaching the Word, and ſo in <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> the Scripture is plain for this, and the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts cannot deny it.</p>
               <p>Or, if you pleaſe to take Mr. <hi>Tho. Hook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi>'s diſtinction, There is an <hi>Inward</hi> and an <hi>Outward</hi> Covenant. [<hi>Cov. of Grace, p.</hi> 2.3.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inward,</hi> ſtanding in a ſpiritual Inſtitution of it between God and man.</p>
               <p>When God calls a people, and with his Call gives them Faith to anſwer his Call: So that now he is indeed their God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes theirs by Faith, and they who are thus in Covenant with him ſhall never fall.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, The outward Covenant is more large; The Diſpenſation of this God gives on his part to Chriſtians, and their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements on their part, is Faith in him, ſubjection to him: He doth engage him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to them, and if they anſwer the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Priviledge, he will make them a choice people, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.5. <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.17, 18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> too long to tranſcribe.</p>
               <p>By vertue of this Covenant, God was ſaid, <hi>To know them above all the Nations in the world,</hi> Amos 3.2. God ſet up <hi>his Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle amongſt them, and dwelt amongſt them,</hi> Exod. 25.8. Pſal. 135.1. <hi>Choſe Iſrael for his peculiar treaſure,</hi> Pſal. 135.4. <hi>Gave them his Ordinances,</hi> Pſal. 147.19, 20. God wrought for them wonderfully; and though they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:32571:24"/>provoked him exceedingly, yet he bare with them, and did not <hi>for</hi> Abraham<hi>'s ſake caſt them out of his preſence as yet,</hi> 2 King. 13.23. Thus was he a <hi>God</hi> to them, the whole viſible Church of the <hi>Jews;</hi> by it God gave them a great advantage to lay hold upon God, to become their God, in an <hi>outward Covenant,</hi> in Efficacy, as well as in outward Adminiſtration: This I ſay, by vertue of this <hi>Covenant</hi> with <hi>Abraham,</hi> till, they dealt moſt wickedly with God in Covenant, rejecting Chriſt, the promiſed Seed in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s. Covenant, in whom they ſhould be bleſſed; then God brake Covenant with them, and caſt them off, <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.10, 14.</p>
               <p>As a people may beſaid to be Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſo God their God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. When they acknowledge God to be the onely true God, and their God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When they worſhip him with his own Worſhip onely.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When they profeſs his Truths, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and take his Word for their Rule.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When they do Covenant and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage themſelves to God. Yet among theſe may be many Hypocrites, and but formal Chriſtians; as <hi>Branches are ſaid to be in Chriſt,</hi> John 15.2.</p>
               <p>My Author moves ſix Queſtions here
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:32571:24"/>to raiſe a duſt, and trouble the Reader, when things are plain; he might have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced them to Three, what is conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the reſt I ſhall touch.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> I call it a <hi>Gracious Covenant:</hi> We read of ſeveral Promiſes God made to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> Gen. 12.2, 3, 7. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 13, 14, 15, 16. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.1, 4, 5. But the word <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> we read not of till this 17th <hi>Chapter,</hi> here we have it ſeveral times: and this Covenant between <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, being the laſt branch of the Covenant [for <hi>Canaan</hi> in the next Verſe, was promiſed three times before] God now adds a Sign, <hi>verſe</hi> 11. which the Apoſtle calls a Seal, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. So that now all the former Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, God binds them up, and ſeals them up in a Covenant. The great Promiſe of all <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.3. <hi>In thy Seed ſhall all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be bleſſed,</hi> is not mentioned in this Chapter, ſince God began to ſpeak of a Covenant; but this was a part of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> tells the <hi>Jews, Acts</hi> 3.25. <hi>Ye are the Children of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which God made with our Fathers, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to</hi> Abrabam, <hi>And in thy Seed ſhall all the Kindreds of the earth be bleſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence that this was a Covenant of Grace, no man can rationally deny. The Apoſtle is ſo clear for it in <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:32571:25"/>
               <p n="1">1. How can God after the breach of the firſt Covenant, now Covenant with any to be their God, but by a Covenant of Grace?</p>
               <p n="2">2. A Covenant in which Chriſt is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and it is confirmed in Chriſt, <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat.</hi> 3.17.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Covenant wherein God preacheth the Goſpel to <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gal. 3.8.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A Covenant, the Righteouſneſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is the Righteouſneſs of Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A Covenant made 430 years, before the Covenant at Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> which <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai</hi> Covenant could not diſanul, <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.17.</p>
               <p>Our Divines have cleared this ſo, that I ſay no more of it; and therefore being <hi>confirmed in Chriſt,</hi> it muſt be the ſame with the new Covenant. But as Chriſt was firſt revealed but obſcurely in a <hi>promiſed Seed,</hi> but afterwards by the Prophets there was a clearer revealing of Chriſt the nearer the time this Son of Righteouſneſs ſhould riſe: So the new Covenant was compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in this Covenant made with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> but by the Prophets afterwards God revealed it more fully, after the <hi>Jews</hi> had ſo violated the Mount <hi>Sinai</hi>-Covenant. Hence that which Divines-call the <hi>Anima faederis,</hi> the Soul of the Covenant, <hi>I will be their God,</hi> was alſo in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:32571:25"/>
               <p>My Author denies that <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and the new Covenant are the ſame; he tells us, <hi>it was a mixed Covenant; there were two Seeds, and ſo Promiſes, and of two ſorts, which muſt he applyed right to the two Seeds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. How many Covenants ſhall we have in the Bible, by this Author? <hi>Camero</hi> is blamed by ſome Divines for making Three Covenants, but by this Author we ſhall have Four. 1. <hi>Adam</hi>'s Covenant, or Covenant of Nature; 2. <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; 3. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Covenant at <hi>Mount Sinai;</hi> 4. The <hi>New Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Are there not outward Promiſes alſo annexed to the <hi>New Covenant,</hi> as well as to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s? Do we not read them plainly?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Are there not two Seeds in your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Baptiſm, to <hi>Adult Perſons</hi> by Dipping; <hi>Real,</hi> and <hi>Formal?</hi> I am ſure they are not all <hi>Real Christians;</hi> and do not your Baptiſm belong to the <hi>New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> a Sign and Seal of the Grace threof? Yet this you Adminiſter to ſuch, as prove Notorious <hi>Hypocrites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Did not <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed by this mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Covenant, enjoy beſides outward Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Bleſſings, thoſe Bleſſings I mentioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in the Church, with more I might have mentioned?</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:32571:26"/>
               <p n="5">5. Did not God engage himſelf to be the God of all the Seed? and did not <hi>Circumciſion</hi> Seal up his Covenant and Engagement to them, if they did perform the Condition? and had they not a great advantage by God's engaging himſelf thus to them to lay hold upon God, for their God and Eternal Portion?</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, <hi>This Covenant was made with</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <hi>as a Believing Perſon, and the Father of Believers;</hi> it was not made with him as a <hi>Man,</hi> nor with his Seed as <hi>Men,</hi> but as the Seed of a <hi>Believing Father. Circumciſion was the Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith.</hi> Rom. 4.11. in which Chapter twice he is called, <hi>The Father of all Believers,</hi> both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles;</hi> and <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29.</p>
               <p>Here a Queſtion might be moved, why <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhould be called, <hi>The Father of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers;</hi> my Reaſon is, were there no <hi>Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi> before <hi>Abraham?</hi> was he the Firſt and Eldeſt <hi>Believer?</hi> The Father in the Family is the firſt in the Family; ſo <hi>Abraham,</hi> if the Father, ſhould be the firſt. But was not <hi>Abel</hi> a <hi>Believer</hi> in <hi>Chriſt, Enoch, Noah,</hi> &amp;c. ſurely there were <hi>Believers</hi> in <hi>Chriſt</hi> a Thouſand Years before <hi>Abraham</hi> was Born, what may we think of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in Charity, may we not think they Believed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:32571:26"/>in the Promiſed Seed? why then ſhould <hi>Abraham</hi> be the <hi>Father?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aquinas</hi> Anſwering to a Queſtion, <hi>Why Circumciſion was commanded firſt to</hi> Abraham, <hi>and to none before?</hi> [<hi>Serm. Doct.</hi> 3. <hi>q.</hi> 70. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.] Anſwers, <hi>That</hi> Abraham <hi>was the firſt that received the Promiſe from God of Chriſt to be born out of his Seed, and the firſt that ſeperated himſelf from the Society of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels.</hi> If this were true, it would ſerve to Anſwer our Queſtion. Tho' <hi>A La ide</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to defend the Vulgar Tranſaction, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>She ſhall bruiſe thy Head;</hi> yet he ſaith it come all to one. <hi>For it is the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man by her Seed, that is Chriſt, that bruiſed the Serpents Head;</hi> Do we think the Lord did not teach his Servants then the uſe and end of the Sacrifices? So that Chriſt was promiſed before, and there were Believers before, if there were a little more revealing of Chriſt to <hi>Abraham</hi> now, that is all. I do more admire his Act in ſacrificing his Son <hi>Iſaac,</hi> though that is given to his <hi>fear of God,</hi> Gen. 22.12.</p>
               <p>I cannot think of any better reaſon than this, though there were Believers in Chriſt, and <hi>Abraham</hi> might be a ſtronger Believer, but with none did God make an expreſs Covenant, <hi>a Believer and his Seed,</hi> and ſeal the Covenant to his Poſterity, but with <hi>Abraham</hi> only.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:32571:27"/>
               <p>I ſhall add a few more words preſently.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>This Covenant was made alſo with, and ſealed to his Seed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The great Queſtion is, who are this <hi>Seed?</hi> my Author tells me, His <hi>Spiritual Seed:</hi> Whence I meet with this once and again, That <hi>Abraham's</hi> natural Seed was a Type of the ſpiritual Seed; Elect, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate. Thus in anſwer to the queſtion, <hi>Whether not baptizing Infants makes not the Priviledge under the Goſpel, leſs than under the Law?</hi> He anſwers, <hi>The natual Seed of</hi> Abraham <hi>was a typical ſhadowing thing— as the Antitype exceeds the Type, the ſpiritual birth the carnal birth; ſo much are we bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. What do you mean by, <hi>ſo much are we better?</hi> Were none of theſe who were Circumciſed being <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Seed, alſo his ſpiritual Seed? Your words carried it as if not. Beſides here would be a queſtion, <hi>How the Elect-regenerate, the ſpiritual Seed, are</hi> Abraham's <hi>Seed; how is he a Father to them, as ſuch?</hi> I am ſure they are <hi>Chriſt's Seed,</hi> Iſa. 53.10, 11. And we can give reaſons, why they ſhould be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>his Seed.</hi> he is the <hi>meritorious</hi> and <hi>effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſe</hi> of them, but <hi>Abraham neither way:</hi> You would have done well to have ſhewn us this. <hi>Abraham</hi> is not ſo much a
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:32571:27"/>Father to us, as <hi>Paul</hi> was to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.15. neither I am ſure in this reſpect he was Father to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> he did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey Faith in his Generation of <hi>Iſaac;</hi> how then is he a Father to us now? That there were Believers before <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.4, 5, 7. Inſtance in <hi>Abel, Enoch,</hi> and <hi>Noah;</hi> (and more I doubt not) but yet in the Hiſtory written by <hi>Moſes, Abraham</hi> is the firſt perſon who is called a <hi>Believer,</hi> upon a ſpecial Promiſe given to him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.6. if any cauſe, he was but <hi>Cauſa exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaris,</hi> which is <hi>Cauſa adjuvnans</hi> to the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal: By his example we ſhould be ſtirred up to believe the Promiſe of God, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> our Father did;
<note n="(a)" place="margin">An exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple how God will juſtifie us.</note> but he had ſuch an advantage as we have not: he knew the Promiſe was made to <hi>him</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, without any diſcourſe, which we cannot know, but muſt firſt prove the Condition. But this I think alſo is a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, He was the <hi>firſt perſon ſealed,</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Seal of that Promiſe or Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and all his Seed after him command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to receive and obſerve the ſame. This Sign and Seal being <hi>viſible,</hi> I conceive <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> is to be conſidered, as a <hi>viſible-belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Father,</hi> and all his <hi>viſible Seed</hi> muſt be ſealed as the Father.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:32571:28"/>
               <p n="2">2. As to what you ſay, the <hi>natural Seed</hi> are the Type of the <hi>ſpiritual Seed;</hi> was not <hi>Iſaac</hi> his natural Seed, and was he not alſo his ſpiritual Seed; then it ſeems <hi>Iſaac</hi> was a Type of himſelf. So all the godly <hi>Jews</hi> after, that were <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed after the fleſh, were Types of themſelves. I pray tell us how the Type and Anti-type meet in one individual perſon? To what Topick in Logick will you refer the Type and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-type?</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, When the Anti-type comes, the Type ceaſe: When then <hi>Iſaac, Jacob,</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that are the natural Seed, come to be the Spiritual Seed, then they muſt ceaſe to be his natural Seed: But how is this poſſible? When Chriſt came, the Types ceaſed.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly, When you Dip your Regenerate perſons; actual Believers you think they are: then they are the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> you judge; then <hi>Abraham</hi> is their Father; then God <hi>is their God:</hi> but divers of theſe are Hypocrites, we know they have proved ſo, and we ſhall hear an Anabaptiſt anon acknowledge it: they profeſſed they took him for their God, and worſhipped him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> while they then lived in your Churches, and did not as yet openly diſcover them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; was <hi>God in no ſenſe their God?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:32571:28"/>
               <p n="4">4ly, To whom Chriſt is a Head, to them God may be ſaid to be a God: But Chriſt is the Head of the viſible Church, in which are many unſound Members; <hi>Branches in him that bear no fruit,</hi> John 15.2. Then God in ſome ſenſe is their God, if Chriſt may in ſome ſenſe be their Head.</p>
               <p n="5">5ly, Is there not an external and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Adoption? <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4. to them <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Adoption:</hi> Were they not called <hi>God's children?</hi> Deut. 14.1. Is not God then the God of his children? Do not God ſay, <hi>They are mine?</hi> Ezek. 16.20, 21. and yet is God no way their God?</p>
               <p n="6">6ly, If the <hi>ſpiritual Seed</hi> be there onely meant, then all the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> were the <hi>ſpiritual Seed;</hi> which I anſwer is falſe. That they muſt be ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your interpretation, the next Verſe proves it; <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 8, 9. At the 8th verſe, <hi>I will give unto thee and to thy ſeed after thee, the I and wherein thou art a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, all the Land of</hi> Canaan <hi>for an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poſſeſſion.</hi> And I will be their God: <hi>Thou ſhalt therefore keep my Covenant, thou and thy ſeed after thee in their generations.</hi> Can the Holy One ſpeak plainer than he doth? Doth he not tell you, that that ſeed of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> which ſhall inherit the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> [where his Tabernacle and all
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:32571:29"/>his Inſtituted Worſhip was ſet up] and there kept the Seal of his Covenant, that he will be <hi>their God?</hi> Doth not God ſpeak the ſame, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10, 11, 12, 13. to the men, women and children, who then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into Covenant with God. <hi>That he may eſtabliſh thee to day for a people unto himſelf:</hi> And that he may be a God unto thee, as he hath ſaid unto thee, <hi>and as he hath ſworn to thy Fathers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Peter</hi> would draw the <hi>Jews</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Chriſt Crucified, who as yet were Unbelievers, and not turned from their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquities, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.25, 26. Do he not uſe this Argument, <hi>You are the children of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which God made with our Fathers;</hi> Abraham <hi>in thy ſeed ſhall all the kindreds of the earth be bleſſed.</hi> This part of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was moſt proper to the thing <hi>Peter</hi> had in hand. But if they were now the children of that Covenant God made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> then God was their God, though as yet they were not a <hi>ſpiritual ſeed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to this <hi>Seed</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> tell us, <hi>The Seed of</hi> Iſhmael <hi>is excepted from Circumciſion;</hi> as it is written; <hi>For in</hi> Iſaac <hi>ſhall thy ſeed be called to thee,</hi> Gen 11.12. <hi>And</hi> Eſau <hi>is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, for lo,</hi> Iſaac <hi>ſaid to</hi> Jacob, <hi>and he give to thee the bleſſing of</hi> Abraham, <hi>to thee and to thy ſeed,</hi> Gen. 28.4. <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was caſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:32571:29"/>out of the Church. Profane <hi>Eſau</hi> deſpiſed his Birth-right, and is caſt off.</p>
               <p>As to the Sons <hi>Abraham</hi> had by <hi>Keturah,</hi> though the Scripture doth not ſay they they were circumciſed, yet we may rather think they were. But whether after <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> had ſent them away, they kept up Circumciſion in their Families, [<hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> kept up Circumciſion we know] and taught their Children the ſpiritual meaning of it, the Scripture is ſilent. So that from them we can draw no Argument <hi>pro</hi> or <hi>con.</hi> This is enough for me, that when God ſaith, <hi>I will ſtabliſh my Covenant between me and thee, and thy ſeed after thee, —To be a God unto thee, and to thy ſeed after thee.</hi> And the very next words, God promiſeth to give the Land of <hi>Canaan to his ſeed, and will be their God there.</hi> And theſe were the Seed of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the Seed of <hi>Jacob;</hi> and as the <hi>Martyr Stephen</hi> calls them, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.38. the Church of God in the Wilderneſs, [that is, <hi>Eccleſia inſtituta, vel organica,</hi> though God might have ſome belong to him that ſprung from the other Sons of <hi>Abraham.</hi>] This is plain and clear, but I am ſure all theſe were not the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſeed.</p>
               <p n="7">7ly, Elect-regenerate ſtand upon even ground with <hi>Abraham,</hi> but here God puts
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:32571:30"/>ſome honour upon <hi>Abraham,</hi> that his ſee ſhall have a bleſſing for his ſake.</p>
               <p n="8">8ly, If Elect-regenerate be only mean by the <hi>Seed,</hi> then there needed not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> word <hi>Seed</hi> to be put in, unleſs you will ſay, God is not the God of Elect-regene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rate, unleſs they be <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed; wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he not of <hi>Abel, Enoch. Noah,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="9">9ly, <hi>This Covenant with</hi> Abraham <hi>and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſeed was ſigned and ſealed,</hi> Gen. 17.9, 10, 11, 12. What <hi>Moſes</hi> calls a Sign, or Token the Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. calls a <hi>Seal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Author tells me, <hi>Circumciſion was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Seal to</hi> Abraham <hi>only, not to Believers, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> their ſeed. To Infants it was a ſign put i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> their fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. too tedious to tranſcribe all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> You tell us, it ſealed to <hi>Abraham onely</hi> the Truth of that Promiſe, <hi>That in his ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all the Familes ſhould be bleſſed.</hi> But the ſame Promiſe was made to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> Gen. 26.4. and to <hi>Jacob,</hi> Gen. 28.14. Did it not ſeal to them as well? Yea, the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> Acts 3.25. tells the <hi>Jews,</hi> they <hi>were children of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant God made with our fathers, ſaying to</hi> Abraham, <hi>And in thy ſeed ſhall all the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reds of the earth be bleſſed.</hi> Did dot Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion ſeal this to them as well? The end of Seals is to <hi>confirm</hi> Faith: had not they, have not we need to have our Faith ſtrenthned? Is the Anabaptiſts Faith ſo
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:32571:30"/>ſtrong, that they need no Seals?</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, I took God's <hi>Signs</hi> to be <hi>Seals,</hi> by the Apoſtle's Authority: I look on the Rain-bow which God calls, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.12, 13. the <hi>Token,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> [the ſame word uſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.11. of Circumciſion] of his Covenant, to be not only a Sign, but a Seal of his Covenant, that he will not drown the World.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly. But why do you ſay, it ſealed that Promiſe; What did it ſeal nothing but that? That Promiſe is not mentioned in this Chapter, but in the 12th, and 22th; but in this Chapter, ſo ſoon as the Lord had made the Covenant between himſelf, <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his Seed, immediately the the Lord adds this Circumciſion, and calls it his Covenant. I am ſure it ſeals this, and I doubt not but the <hi>Jews</hi> did ſo look upon it, as a Seal of the Covenant between God and them; that God was their God, and they his people.</p>
               <p>Sir, you muſt give me better grounds than theſe, or elſe I muſt ſtill be of the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the great body of the moſt learned and pious Divines; <hi>viz. That all the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of the Old and New Teſtament, were and are Signs of the Covenant, ſealing up the Grace of God to Believers.</hi> My Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:32571:31"/>hath more Notions about Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: but of them afterwards.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the Child, Circumciſion left a ſignal Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,</hi> ſaith he.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. That which you call a ſignal Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, God calls his Covenant. But</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, Though there were a ſignal Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion left in the Infant, yet if when it came to years it were not taught the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual meaning of it, the Child would get no benefit by it.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly, What ſignal Impreſſion is left upon thoſe whom you baptize by Dipping, when <hi>Adult,</hi> more than upon thoſe who are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized by pouring of Water upon them when Infants? True, you can remember better you were dipped; but Children, tho' they have but a moral certainty from their Parents and others, and the Teſtimony of the Book in which they are recorded, yet being taught the meaning of it, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if as ſome Parents who compoſe ſhort Prayers for their Children, put in that Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, for the bleſſing of their Baptiſm, as ſome Parents do; Children may keep it in mind, and in time come to make as good uſe of it, as thoſe who are dipped when <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dult;</hi> and Experience I hope will prove it.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:32571:31"/>
               <p n="4">4ly, If that be true which Mr. <hi>Tom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> is willing to believe out of Mr. <hi>Selden,</hi> that the <hi>Jews</hi> admitted <hi>Proſelites,</hi> by <hi>Baptiſm</hi> the female kind, the ſame Author <hi>Mr. Selden,</hi> and ſo <hi>Baxter</hi> tells us, the Children alſo of the <hi>Proſelites</hi> were admitted by <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> to what purpoſe ſaith the <hi>Anaba tiſt,</hi> ſince they underſtand it not, and there is no Impreſſion left? Let the <hi>Jews</hi> anſwer that.</p>
               <p n="5">5ly, <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed being ſo nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous as the Stars in the Heavens, how could the Infants circumciſed, when they came to riper years, and living only in <hi>Canaan,</hi> know that there was any Signal Impreſſion made upon their fleſh, unleſs their Parents or others told them: might not they well think al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> men were as they, or it might be proper to their Nation? If they then were certain by their Parents and others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming them, cannot we be as certain by our Parents Information, that we were baptized?</p>
               <p n="6">6ly, May there not be a Conveyance of a great <hi>Eſtate</hi> to a <hi>Child</hi> that lies in the Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and underſtand nothing many years; but when it comes to ripe years, and ſee its Name in the Conveyance, and the Witneſſes, now it can ſue for it. Two things are very deſirable, if there were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to trouble the Conſcience [a thing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:32571:32"/>to be lamented] and other things concur. Firſt, That <hi>Baptiſm</hi> ſhould ever be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in the face of the Church. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, The Names of all baptized Recorded; [both which I have known the conſtant practice in Independent Churches:] By both which, and Parents Education, a Child when it comes to years of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, may be as ſure of its <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> though it makes no Impreſſion as Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion did in the fleſh, and now ſue out the Bleſſings which there the Lord did ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, and conditionally ſeal to be mine.</p>
               <p n="7">7ly, Were our Churches in that order they ought to be; and were that laudable Practice [which certainly is our Duty] taken up, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſpecial care b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> taken, that Children baptized be diligently Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chized, and when they come to fit years, be called before the Elderſhip, there to own their Baptiſmal Covenant, and give an account of their Faith; ſolemn Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er made for them, and the Church now to take care of them, and inſpection over them, as being their Members; there would be no room for this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, and leſs ground for <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> to cry down <hi>Infant-baptiſm.</hi> If we will keep Churches [ſo far as our Duty can reach] for Chriſt, it is not preaching a Sermon
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:32571:32"/>or two on the <hi>Lord's-Day,</hi> will do the work, there is more required than ſo.</p>
               <p>Though the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſtrength lie in the incapacity of Infants to believe in Chriſt, yet becauſe this notion hath been a trouble to me heretofore, therefore I ſpeak the more to it.</p>
               <p n="5">5ly, <hi>This Covenant never repealed by God.</hi> Now I come to the Pinch: Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> the greateſt Adverſary that ever the Seed of Believers had, yields two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That the Children of the</hi> Jews <hi>were Members with their Parents in the Jewiſh Church.</hi> [But then, ſay I, it muſt be by vertue of this Parental-Covenant God made with <hi>Abraham;</hi> elſe how they ſhould be Members with their Parents, I know not.]</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, <hi>That if the Children of believing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, be Members of the Church with the Parents, then they muſt be baptized. For I grant,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that Baptiſm is the way and manner of ſolemn Admiſſion into the Church, I mean the regular way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then the Queſtion muſt be thus ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>When the</hi> Jews <hi>believed in Chriſt, come, crucified, riſen, and aſcended, as the five thouſand in</hi> Acts 4.4. <hi>Did the Lord now repeal his Covenant which he made with</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:32571:33"/>Abraham <hi>and his Seed; admit only the Parents into the Goſpel-Church, but bar the Doors against their Poſterity, or Children?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I think I have ſtated the Queſtion right, and if this cannot be proved, then I hope believing <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhall find a way to bring in their Children too with the <hi>Jews,</hi> and find a Title to Baptiſm by Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi>'s Conceſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Affirmanti incumbit probatio;</hi> This lie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> to prove. And here though I am far from that abſurd, irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Principle of <hi>Veronius,</hi> who lays down this for a Rule in our Diſputation with the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> That we muſt bring ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Scriptures to confute them, yet this caſting all the Poſterity of the Godly out of the Church, is ſo <hi>wretched a Doctrine,</hi> [as Mr. <hi>Thomas Hooker</hi> calls it] againſt the poor Infants, that as yet want a Tongue to plead for themſelves, that the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> muſt bring Scriptures, if not expreſs, yet as clear and ſtrong as expreſs Scriptures, elſe I ſhall little regard their Writings. And this I require upon theſe grounds.</p>
               <p>Firſt, The <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> require of us an expreſs Command from Chriſt to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, to baptize Infants. This was put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me in the Congregation: Now it is meet the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſhould be honeſt men,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:32571:33"/>buy and ſell by the ſame meaſure. If they require of us expreſs Scriptures, we may well require of them the ſame.</p>
               <p>Secondly, All the Arguments which the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> draw from Scripture againſt Infants Church-memberſhip, and Baptiſm, do ſtrike at the Grace and Wiſdom of God in his Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, and his Conſtitution of the Church of the <hi>Jews,</hi> as if the Lord had not done wiſely, but they will teach him how to Conſtitute Churches better. We ſhall hear their Arguments anon.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The holy Page tells us, how much weight the <hi>Jews</hi> and falſe Teachers put upon Circumciſion, what a ſtir it made in the Churches, while the Apoſtles la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to remove it, though it was a pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full bloody Ordinance. We read <hi>Acts</hi> 21.21. This was the great Objection againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> and this was 21 years after <hi>Paul</hi>'s Converſion: I am apt to think till the <hi>Temple</hi> [the head of all the Ceremonies] was utterly demoliſhed; the believing <hi>Jews</hi> did Circumciſe their Children; But had <hi>Paul</hi> told them, the Reaſon was, that Chriſt is come, and now the Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> as to his Seed, is repealed, and their Seed are all <hi>caſt out</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and therefore they muſt not Circumciſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:32571:34"/>their Children: Should we not have read the <hi>Jews</hi> Clamours and Out-cries againſt the Apoſtles, in the <hi>Acts,</hi> and in every E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, and what a bar had this been againſt the reception of the Goſpel; I appeal to the Conſciences of the <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi> But though we read of <hi>Circumciſion</hi> in ſeveral places, both in the <hi>Acts</hi> and the <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> there is not one word of this.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, God did expreſly repeal his Covenant with <hi>Iſrael</hi> made at Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> Heb. 8.13. <hi>That which decayeth and waxeth old is ready to vaniſh away.</hi> This Covenant of God with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, is a Covenant much noted in the Scripture, and long before <hi>Sinai-Covenant:</hi> Now if the Lord doth indeed repeal this Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> why ſhould we not expect clear Scripture-ground. The <hi>Jews</hi> quarrell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the <hi>Apostles,</hi> becauſe they changed the Cuſtoms of <hi>Moſes, Acts</hi> 6.14. &amp; chap. 21. v. 21. but if they had taught the nulling of the Covenant of God with <hi>Abraham</hi> their Father too, the Apoſtles ſhould have heard of it with both ears, and we ſhould have read it. God tells them when he repealed that Covenant, He would make a new Covenant with the <hi>Houſe of Iſrael,</hi> and the <hi>Houſe of Judah:</hi> are not Children a part of the <hi>Houſe?</hi> They were ſo when God made
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:32571:34"/>that Covenant with the <hi>Houſe of Iſrael, Deut.</hi> 29.10, 11, 12. then they are in the <hi>Houſe</hi> ſtill, then they are capable of the Grace of the new Covenant with their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; then the want of actual Faith doth not exclude them from <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, God tells <hi>Abraham,</hi> he will <hi>eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh his Covenant,—and it ſhall be an ever laſting Covenant,</hi> Gen. 17.7. If God <hi>eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh,</hi> it muſt ſtand: If he ſaith, it is <hi>everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> the Entail is not cut off: Nor do I doubt in the leaſt, but as when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected Chriſt, and ſaid, <hi>Let his blood be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us and our children,</hi> Mat. 27.25. God did caſt away Parents and Children: ſo when God receives them again, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.15.26. the Parents ſhall not be received, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren remain caſt out, but they ſhall come in with their Parents.</p>
               <p>If they ſay, the word <hi>Everlaſting,</hi> is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of their poſſeſſion of <hi>Canaan,</hi> verſe 8. and <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> v. 13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I know well how the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>for ever,</hi> or <hi>everlaſting</hi> is taken in Scripture, but it doth not at all hinder the Argument.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For in this Covenant is nothing <hi>Typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> it is pure Grace; and we have other Scriptures in the Goſpel will confirm it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As to Circumciſion, it was a <hi>bloody Ordinance,</hi> as was the <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> all <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:32571:35"/>ſo, till Chriſt came with his <hi>Blood</hi> fulfilling all, removed them: No more <hi>blood</hi> in any <hi>Ordinance</hi> after Chriſt. <hi>Zippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> calls <hi>Moſes</hi> a <hi>bloody Husband,</hi> at the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſing of her Son, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.25, 26. At this time when the <hi>Jews</hi> circumciſe their Children; they ſay they may do it from Sun-riſing to Sun-ſetting, any hour on the Eighth day: but they chooſe the Morning, becauſe the Child then being empty, it will not bleed ſo much: The <hi>Mohet,</hi> or he that circumciſeth, ſucks the Wound three times, and uſe other means to ſtop the <hi>blood,</hi> but no <hi>bloody Ordinance</hi> now. [<hi>Buxt. Synor. Iſid.</hi> p. 81.86.]</p>
               <p n="3">3. For the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> that was conditional, their abiding in it; but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, though they are now caſt out of poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, yet they have <hi>jus ad rem,</hi> a juſt Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to it at this day. Hence <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.14.21. &amp; <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.24. Three times the Lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to <hi>bring them into their own Land,</hi> ver. 28. the Promiſe runs for them. It is <hi>their own; then now to depart from the literal ſenſe, without ſome eminent abſurdity that will follow upon the literal ſenſe, we ought not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6ly, If God will not bring an <hi>unclean Creature</hi> forbidden, into a <hi>believing Jew's Houſe,</hi> without an <hi>expreſs word</hi> to <hi>warrant it,</hi> will God caſt a <hi>holy Seed</hi> out of <hi>his Houſe,</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:32571:35"/>and not give as <hi>clear a ground</hi> to the <hi>belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Parent</hi> to know his <hi>mind?</hi> The <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Creatures</hi> ſignifying the <hi>Heathen</hi> of ſeveral ſorts, [the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſay, <hi>Babylonians, Medes, Perſians, Greeks, Romans] not eat;</hi> that is, not to have <hi>communion,</hi> Acts 10.28. Compare <hi>Levit.</hi> 11.5, 6, 7. with <hi>Acts</hi> 10.11, 12, 13, 15. and muſt now the <hi>holy Seed</hi> be caſt out of the Church, and looked upon as the <hi>Swine</hi> were then? We muſt have <hi>clearer grounds</hi> and <hi>Texts,</hi> than ever yet the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> have brought, I ſay as ſtrong as <hi>expreſs Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7ly, The <hi>New Teſtament</hi> doth give us <hi>clear Texts</hi> to prove the <hi>Church-memberſhip</hi> of <hi>believing Parents;</hi> you cannot give us <hi>clearer Texts</hi> for their <hi>unchurching,</hi> unleſs you give us <hi>expreſs Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8ly, Let me take up one of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Arguments,</hi> and improve it my way.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If God hath repeled his Covenant, and caſt the Seed of the believing Jews out of the Church, then it was either in juſtice or in mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But neither this nor that; therefore not caſt out,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>thus Mr.</hi> Baxter.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, not in <hi>juſtice,</hi> I prove thus. Let <hi>Parents</hi> be never ſuch <hi>ſound Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> walk in <hi>the ſteps of their Father Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> keep cloſe in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> yet the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> caſt out all their <hi>Seed;</hi> but this
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:32571:36"/>cannot be in <hi>juſtice:</hi> for the <hi>Text</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.10. <hi>All the paths of the Lord are mercy and truth unto ſuch as keep his Covenant.</hi> But theſe <hi>Jews, believing Parents</hi> do ſo; yet God repeals his <hi>Covenant</hi> with their <hi>Seed,</hi> and caſt them out of the Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>In mercy</hi> the Lord <hi>doth it not; For then God gives a greater mercy in the room of that which in mercy he takes away,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is true what Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſaith, I prove what he ſaith, the <hi>believing Jew</hi> ſhall ſay, though God hath repealed his <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> with my <hi>Seed,</hi> and caſt them out of the Church, yet he hath given my <hi>Seed</hi> a <hi>better mercy,</hi> both my ſelf and my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, if they could ſpeak, would ſay, <hi>We would not be under</hi> Abraham<hi>'s Covenant with our Parents, nor</hi> Church-Members <hi>with our Parents, as we were before Chriſt came, for Chriſt hath left us Infants a better Bleſſing in the room.</hi> As it was a <hi>great favour</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that <hi>God gave his Oracles to them,</hi> Pſalm 147.19, 28. That <hi>God was in Covenant with them, Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. But God will <hi>null that Covenant,</hi> Heb. 8.13. It ſhall <hi>vaniſh away:</hi> But God will make <hi>another Covenant, new,</hi> a <hi>better Covenant,</hi> having <hi>better Promiſes</hi> in the room of <hi>that old va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing Covenant:</hi> So that if <hi>Iſraels eyes be opened,</hi> they would ſay, <hi>they would by no
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:32571:36"/>means be under the old Covenant, this new is ſo much better.</hi> Thus let the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> tell us what God hath left <hi>better</hi> for the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Seed</hi> of a <hi>Jew</hi> now <hi>believing in Chriſt,</hi> that now it would not be <hi>Church-member</hi> with the <hi>Parents,</hi> nor under <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Covenant,</hi> nor would now be <hi>baptized,</hi> as before Chriſt they were <hi>circumciſed:</hi> For my part I can conceive nothing; keep to the ſtate of the Queſtion.</p>
               <p n="9">9. There is <hi>ſo much evil</hi> in this <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> that we muſt have <hi>clearer Scriptures</hi> than ever were produced as yet to prove it, and clear it from <hi>that evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As 1. For the bleſſed God; How doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>diſhonour him in ſtraitning his Love and Grace now under the Goſpel,</hi> over it was <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law. Moſes</hi> tells the <hi>Jews,</hi> Deut. 4.37. <hi>The Lord loved thy Fathers,</hi> Chap. 7.8. &amp; chap. 33.3. So it appears, <hi>that he would not only take the Fathers, but their Children alſo into Covenant, and conſtitute his Church of them alſo.</hi> But now whatever the Goſpel ſaith of the <hi>Philanthropie of God, Tit.</hi> 3.4. and <hi>God ſo loving the world,</hi> Joh. 16.3. when that <hi>Seed</hi> promiſed to <hi>Abraham</hi> is come, <hi>in whom all Nations ſhall be bleſſed,</hi> he <hi>nulls</hi> the <hi>Covenant</hi> with his <hi>Seed,</hi> caſt them out of the Church, and leaves no <hi>bleſſing for their
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:32571:37"/>Infants,</hi> when their <hi>Parents believe in the promiſed Seed</hi> come.</p>
               <p>Before the Lord calls the little <hi>children under the Covenant,</hi> and <hi>in the Church, (Mine)</hi> Ezek. 16.20, 21. But now the <hi>Jews believe in Chriſt,</hi> God calls <hi>none</hi> of their Children <hi>Mine,</hi> though now they do more gladly <hi>bear them unto him</hi> than they did before.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, It <hi>diſhonours Chriſt;</hi> He <hi>took upon him indeed the Seed of</hi> Abraham, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.16. and turned the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> out of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> and out of the <hi>Church,</hi> if the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts Doctrine be true.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though he ſeemed to have an <hi>affection</hi> to <hi>Children,</hi> and was much <hi>diſpleaſed</hi> with his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> when they rebuked the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> when they came to ſeek his <hi>bleſſing for their Babes,</hi> Mark 10. 13, 14. and bad them bring their <hi>children to him,</hi> and told them, of <hi>ſuch is the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> If our ſweet Lord <hi>meant</hi> as he <hi>ſpake,</hi> and we <hi>believe he did,</hi> then they are ſtill <hi>Members of the Church,</hi> he doth not ſhut the <hi>Door againſt them, now he is come.</hi> But the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> tell us a <hi>contrary Tale</hi> to the <hi>diſhonour</hi> of our <hi>bleſſed Saviour.</hi> When the <hi>belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Jews</hi> now carry their <hi>children</hi> to Chriſt, Dedicate them to him with earneſt Prayer <hi>in Baptiſm,</hi> and ingage to bring them up
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:32571:37"/>for him, the <hi>Anabaptiſts forbid them,</hi> and tell them, <hi>the Kingdom of Heaven doth not conſiſt of ſuch little Ones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Per abſurdum vero eſt, ut per Meſſiae adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum imminutum ſit foedus ſanctu,</hi> Voſſius. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. That the <hi>bleſſed,</hi> and <hi>bleſſing, Meſſia,</hi> by his <hi>coming,</hi> ſhould <hi>null the Covenant</hi> with <hi>Abraham,</hi> it is <hi>not only abſurd,</hi> but <hi>very ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd,</hi> a great <hi>reproach</hi> is caſt upon Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Doctor <hi>Thomas Goodwin</hi> pleading the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant's caſe</hi> againſt the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> ſaith, <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>In a manner half the Church of God, the pureſt part of it; Elect Infants die in their bud and infancy, and grow not up to partake of the dews and influence of any other outward Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance; and were they deprived of this,</hi> [i.e. <hi>Baptiſm</hi>] <hi>ſhould go out of this world [into which God only ſent them to receive that which ſhould make them meet for the common Inheritance of the Saints] without any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward owning them, or viſible way of bleſſing from him,</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>yea and the other half that grow up to glorifie God in their riper years, whereof many alſo are holy from the Womb; theſe alſo ſhould, during their years of nonage, want an outward badg, and any outward ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of what they are, even Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heirs of the Kingdom with their Brethren, which even in the Infancy of the World, whilst all were under Tutors and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:32571:38"/>was their priviledge.</hi>
                  </q> Thus this <hi>Goſpel-Divine</hi> ſpeaks, and that to the purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly, As to <hi>Parents,</hi> be they never ſo <hi>godly,</hi> what <hi>grief</hi> muſt it needs be to them, if their <hi>children</hi> die out of the <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>viſible Church;</hi> what <hi>hopes</hi> can they have of their <hi>Salvation,</hi> more than an <hi>Indian</hi> hath of his being both in the ſame ſtate? An <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian-child</hi> may be <hi>Elected</hi> as well as a ſound <hi>Believer.</hi> 2ly, nor can a <hi>believing Parent</hi> pray for his <hi>children</hi> upon any <hi>grounds</hi> more than an <hi>Indian:</hi> the <hi>Covenant and Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> ſcattered in the World to the <hi>Godly</hi> and their <hi>Seed,</hi> they <hi>cannot</hi> plead upon them. 3ly, Whereas the <hi>Covenant</hi> and the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement</hi> of the <hi>children</hi> to God in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> is the <hi>Infant's Circumciſion,</hi> might be <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> to <hi>whet</hi> upon their <hi>children,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them: now no ſuch <hi>Arguments</hi> are in <hi>date.</hi> 4ly, The <hi>Jews</hi> before Chriſt came, in the day of their <hi>circumciſing their Infants,</hi> did uſe to give <hi>thanks to God,</hi> and <hi>bleſs him</hi> for <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Covenant,</hi> and his <hi>Ordinance</hi> of <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> the <hi>Seal</hi> of his <hi>Covenant:</hi> but when the <hi>Jews</hi> believe Chriſt's <hi>come,</hi> now <hi>Thanksgiving and bleſſing of God</hi> ceaſe; for the <hi>Govenant</hi> is <hi>nulled, children</hi> caſt out of the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4ly, As for the <hi>Children of believing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> if they come <hi>to years of diſcretion,</hi> and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:32571:38"/>God bleſs <hi>Parents inſtructions</hi> ſo as to keep <hi>Conſcience awake,</hi> though they play the <hi>wretches,</hi> and have cauſe to be humbled all their days; yet I ſay, if <hi>Conſcience</hi> be kept <hi>awake,</hi> and God begin to open their Eyes more, and make them in <hi>earneſt</hi> to mind the <hi>Salvation</hi> of their <hi>Souls,</hi> then they will underſtand what a <hi>wretched Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> this <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> is, by <hi>denying that to them</hi> by which they may take hold of God in the time of their fears. <hi>Quare patet non prorſus vanum eſſe atque inane ex pio genere naſci,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter Martyn,</hi> [Hoc Com. p. 8.] It is not a vain empty thing to be <hi>born of godly Parents:</hi> this is true which he ſaith.</p>
               <p>Here, tho' it was far from my thoughts to ſpeak, much leſs to write what <hi>benefit</hi> I have <hi>experimentally found</hi> from a <hi>Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal-Covenant,</hi> and <hi>Infant-Baptiſm;</hi> yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Lord's Providence</hi> hath engaged me in this <hi>Controverſie,</hi> which I never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and becauſe it may be a help to others, <hi>Children of good Parents,</hi> I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare.</p>
               <p>God bleſſed my <hi>godly Parents Education</hi> of me, to keep my <hi>Conſcience awake,</hi> as I ſaid, though I have cauſe to <hi>abhor my ſelf</hi> all my days; but above fifty years paſt, I began to have more <hi>ſerious thoughts</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:32571:39"/>about an <hi>eternal ſtate,</hi> and how to get an <hi>Intereſt in Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Promiſes.</hi> I found <hi>ſeveral qualifications</hi> that did prepare hearts for <hi>Promiſes,</hi> Iſa. 61.1. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Luke</hi> 19.10. My trouble for ſome years, now how to make out theſe <hi>qualifications:</hi> I would have them, prayed for them, but could not ſatisſie my ſelf that I had them as I ought to have them. While I was writing my Copy, theſe very words, there comes to me a good <hi>chriſtian woman,</hi> who I know for many years had walked with God, and ſhe puts this <hi>Queſtion</hi> to me, <hi>How ſhe might know whether ſhe ever had theſe qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications,</hi> in Mat. 11.28. and engaged me to ſend <hi>one Exerciſe</hi> upon it, as I did: I could not but take notice of this <hi>Providence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>While I was thus troubled about ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out theſe <hi>qualifications,</hi> there comes a <hi>motion</hi> into my <hi>mind; What ſay you to your Father's Covenant?</hi> You know your <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> were <hi>godly,</hi> and God promiſed <hi>to be the God of</hi> Abraham <hi>and his ſeed;</hi> will you ſtand to your <hi>Father's Covenant,</hi> and chooſe your <hi>Father's God</hi> for your God? I began to think of it, my heart anſwered, <hi>Yes, I will ſtand to my Father's Covenant:</hi> But how do you take your <hi>Father's God to be your God?</hi> I anſwered, <hi>As he was my Father's God.</hi> My teaching <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od,</hi> my heart-hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:32571:39"/>
                  <hi>God,</hi> my reconciled <hi>God,</hi> my juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying <hi>God,</hi> my ſanctifying <hi>God,</hi> my <hi>God</hi> to lead me all my days; for thus he was my <hi>Father's God.</hi> Here my <hi>qualification</hi> was the <hi>choice</hi> of my <hi>Father's God,</hi> who was mine before by an <hi>external Covenant-admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration;</hi> but now to have him <hi>my God, my portion,</hi> by an <hi>internal Covenant</hi> and <hi>effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy?</hi> Here now I was pent up; <hi>Will you chooſe him, or refuſe him?</hi> Bleſſed be God who gave me this <hi>advantage</hi> to lay hold up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, by virtue of this <hi>Parental-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Further, to clear my <hi>meaning,</hi> Ido not by this <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> about <hi>Qualifications of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,</hi> intend that Chriſtians ſhould not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard them. I am far from that: if they be <hi>ſound Chriſtians,</hi> I'le warrant them they ſhall regard them. Nor do I think but Chriſtians reflecting upon themſelves, the <hi>good Spirit aſſiſting,</hi> may find them <hi>certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrought.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this I mean, <hi>Young perſons</hi> brought up under the <hi>droppings</hi> of <hi>good Education,</hi> upon whom God works more <hi>gradually;</hi> that cannot tell the <hi>time when,</hi> nor the <hi>manner how God works;</hi> as ſome Adult per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons upon whom God many times breaks in with his <hi>Terrours;</hi> theſe uſe to be much troubled about the making out the <hi>qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:32571:40"/>of Inviting Promiſes,</hi> becauſe they cannot find them ſo ſenſibly as they would, though they have them <hi>in truth,</hi> but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>diſcern it:</hi> the queſtion is, <hi>Whether now</hi> Abraham<hi>'s Covenant may not do ſuch a Soul a pleaſure?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>When God made this Covenant with</hi> Abraham <hi>and his Seed, did not God intend good to</hi> Abraham<hi>'s Seed? If not, it was a vain Covenant? God forbid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To ſay, it ſignifies no more than that, when he gave <hi>them his Oracles,</hi> Rom. 3.2. Was not that a Priviledge, if his <hi>Seed would improve them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this <hi>Covenant</hi> was <hi>diſtinct</hi> from the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles,</hi> made before the <hi>Oracles were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:</hi> and may not <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Seed? ought</hi> they not to <hi>improve it</hi> to their <hi>ſpiritual good and advantage:</hi> who will deny it?</p>
               <p>God in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.4. ſpeaks of <hi>taking hold of his Covenant.</hi> I ſay, by this <hi>Covenant</hi> God puts forth his hand to <hi>Abraham's Seed</hi> to take hold upon him, ſo as to become their <hi>God for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Suppoſe we two ſorts of perſons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Conviction of a miſerable ſtate:</hi> One ſort is under <hi>Abraham's Covenant,</hi> the other not; There are <hi>Inviting Promiſes</hi> to all ſorts, whether without, or within the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi> They who are within the <hi>Covenant,</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:32571:40"/>can make uſe of all the <hi>Inviting Promiſes</hi> offered to others, and <hi>Abraham's Covenant</hi> too: But they who are out of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> cannot make uſe of, or lay hold upon God by <hi>Abraham's Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2ly, God is <hi>nearer to his Covenanted-ſeed</hi> than to <hi>others,</hi> Pſalm 148.14. <hi>Iſrael a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple near unto the Lord: Iſrael</hi> is in <hi>Covenant</hi> with him: <hi>God loved their Fathers,</hi> Deut. 4.37. By this he puts forth his hand to them to lay hold upon him more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, than to others out of Covenant. The chooſing of their <hi>Father's God</hi> for their <hi>God</hi> in <hi>ſincerity,</hi> is the Condition, and he becomes <hi>their God,</hi> and his Covenant gives them a ground for the <hi>aſſurance of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3ly, This <hi>Covenanted-Seed</hi> may plead with God in <hi>Prayer</hi> for many Promiſes made to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright</hi> and their <hi>Seed,</hi> Pſal. 112.2. Prov. 20.7. with divers other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, fetching the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of their plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Covenant and Promiſes, which others out of the Covenant cannot do. And ſince God hath promiſed <hi>bleſſing</hi> to this <hi>Seed;</hi> the <hi>Seed</hi> may chooſe their <hi>bleſſing,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>ſpiritual bleſſing</hi> in Chriſt, and have his Promiſe to warrant it.</p>
               <p n="4">4ly, When their hearts are in <hi>fears, troubles, doubts,</hi> and cannot make out the <hi>qualifications</hi> of other Promiſes, as they
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:32571:41"/>would, they may come hither: here is no winding out, but anſwer <hi>Catagorice, will you have your Father's God, or refuſe him?</hi> You ſee he offers himſelf, and is in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with you one way already, by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Covenant-adminiſtration; and if you will ſtand to that Covenant, and take him for your God indeed, and yield up your ſelf to him, he will be your God in a ſaving manner, and portion for ever.</p>
               <p n="5">5ly, Since all the Word and Promiſes are then efficacious when the Spirit will pleaſe to work with them; and it is free for him to make this or that Word effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to us: I doubt not to ſay, <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant, is as fit as any inviting Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and it is as rational for the <hi>Seed</hi> of godly Parents to lay hold upon God by it, as by any other Word.</p>
               <p>My Parents then looking upon me as being in Covenant, and a Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber with them, they did Dedicate me to God, and brought me under the Seal of his gracious Covenant in Baptiſm. And what our Lord ſaid to <hi>Peter</hi> when he waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Feet, <hi>John</hi> 13. 6, 7. <hi>What I do thou knoweſt not now, but thou ſhalt know hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> Was truly verified of me. What the Lord did then, when he poured <hi>clean wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> upon me in my <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> I know not,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:32571:41"/>but now I do know, and did many years ſince. What was the opinion of the ancient Fathers, and many Divines now, about the <hi>Efficacy</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> I did not then know, nor do I now concern my ſelf about it, to diſcourſe it. But this I took for a Truth, It doth not conſiſt with the <hi>Infinite wiſdom</hi> and <hi>holineſs of God,</hi> to Inſtitute any <hi>Ordinance</hi> in his <hi>Houſe</hi> that is of <hi>trivial con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment,</hi> whatever they ſeem to be to a <hi>carnal heart:</hi> they are things of <hi>great weight;</hi> Where the great God engages himſelf to a Creature, and therefore to be attended with great <hi>reverence,</hi> and as dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently <hi>improved.</hi> Now when I came to reflect upon my <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> how God was <hi>firſt</hi> with me, before I underſtood him, he was <hi>afore-hand</hi> with me, took hold of me, brought me under the Seal of his bleſſed Covenant; and when I read over the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Texts,</hi> which tells us what <hi>bleſſings</hi> are there <hi>ſignified</hi> and <hi>ſealed,</hi> God was engaged for his part; if I will look to my part, to anſwer the Condition, then theſe ſhould be mine; this gave me encouragement. As for my Dedication to him, I was willing to ſtand to it, I did like it very well: but both for the Condition, and to anſwer my Dedication, I went to him, whoſe Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant it is, and who was <hi>firſt</hi> with me, that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:32571:42"/>he would pleaſe to perform his part, and in the ſtrength of his performance, I would perform my part. Why would that <hi>bleſſed One</hi> be <hi>firſt?</hi> Why did he begin with me, when I did not know him? But ſince he will be a God, and Triumph in his Grace, ſince I came to underſtand it, by his Grace I have held him, and will hold him. And though as I ſaid, I have not <hi>attained</hi> what I ſeek af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet I have found in my diſmal Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, wherein I have had as deep a ſhare as moſt <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ever had, when I could not tell where to lay hold, my <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent al-covenant</hi> and <hi>Infant-baptiſm,</hi> which I am ſtill <hi>improving</hi> now my Head is <hi>gray,</hi> have been a ſupport unto me. So that I bleſs God, 1. for <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Covenant,</hi> 2ly, I bleſs God that I had <hi>godly Parents:</hi> 3ly, I bleſs God my Parents were no <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> but that while I was an <hi>Infant</hi> they brought me under the Seal of the <hi>bleſſed Covenant,</hi> a ſtay and comfort to me in my old age, and I hope <hi>improved,</hi> as well as they who were Dipped yeſterday.</p>
               <p>When people do either not underſtand things, or if they do, yet they do not mind and improve them, ſo get no good by them; no wonder though they talk againſt them, when others bleſs God for them, and daore his grace in them.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:32571:42"/>
               <p>Let the Children of Godly Parents look to themſelves, they have a price in their hands, if they have wiſdom and hearts to improve it; it is a fearful thing to hear of the Child of a Godly, Praying, Parent to dye in an unconverted State.</p>
               <p>Only a word, ſome may think you had Godly Parents, mine were not ſo; it may be I had a Godly Grandfather, or a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: had you ſo? no doubt but you may improve the <hi>Covenant</hi> from him. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Commandement</hi> will help you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>David</hi> pleaded 86 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. <hi>Save the Son of thy Hand-maid:</hi> he pleads the Parental-<hi>Covenant</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Hooker.)</hi> Born thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of Godly Parents, who were thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitors (ſaith <hi>Ainſworth?) Inſignis est priorum praerogativa, qua etiam</hi> David, <hi>hic animum ſuum in precibus fulcit, quod ſciunt ſe in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia a fidelibus Parentibus, qui fuerunt ſervi, &amp; ancillae Domini, natos eſſe.</hi> Saith <hi>Geſnor</hi> on the Text, and ſtirs up Parents to learn this <hi>Treaſure</hi> to their Children; and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of ſuch Parents to make uſe of it. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> alſo ſpeaks well to this Head.</p>
               <p>Others it may be will ſay, <hi>Baptiſed I am, but my Parents bad enough.</hi> Well, art a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, and art in earneſt for Chriſt, and the ſaving Bleſſings come by him? you may improve your <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> When the <hi>Gibeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:32571:43"/>by Craft got <hi>Iſrael</hi> into a <hi>Covenant</hi> with them, and confirmed it by an Oath. 9 <hi>Joſh.</hi> 15. the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to deſtroy them; They were made Servants indeed; the breach of this coſt <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> dear. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.1, 2, 3. If you be got under the Seal of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> it was not by Craft, but God's Providence order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it; and now you are under it, prize it, and improve it; do not you fear, the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> will hold to his part.</p>
               <p>Theſe being the Evils that ariſe from the <hi>Anabaptiſts Doctrine,</hi> we muſt have very clear <hi>Texts,</hi> for the nulling of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Covenant,</hi> and caſting Children out of the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10ly, If <hi>Bleſſed Jeſus</hi> upon his coming doth repeat <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Covenant,</hi> and ſo the Children of the <hi>Believing Jews</hi> be no <hi>Church-Members,</hi> then <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> by his coming doth null the <hi>Promiſes</hi> made to the <hi>Fathers.</hi> But the <hi>Text</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 8. <hi>He confirms the Promiſes made to the Fathers.</hi> I am ſure this was one made to the <hi>Fathers, I will be a God to thee and thy Seed,</hi> then it is not null<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but confirmed. Chriſt confirms <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s <hi>Charter, Act.</hi> 3.26. God ſent his Son <hi>Jeſus</hi> to the <hi>Jews</hi> firſt, to Bleſs them: one great Bleſſing he mentions, but it ſeems by the <hi>Anabaptiſts, Chriſt,</hi> takes away a Bleſſing;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:32571:43"/>tell us I pray what Bleſſing doth <hi>Chriſt</hi> leave the Seed of the <hi>Believing Jews,</hi> while <hi>Infants</hi> in the Room of it.</p>
               <p n="11">11ly, We read <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. of <hi>Promiſes</hi> made to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his <hi>Seed; Promiſes</hi> in the Plural Number, <hi>Seed</hi> in the Singular, not <hi>Seeds;</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> a part, and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> a part, not ſo, but <hi>Seed;</hi> that is, <hi>Chriſt</hi> My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical, not Perſonal: the <hi>Promiſes</hi> were not made to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but <hi>Chriſt</hi> was <hi>Promiſed</hi> to <hi>Abraham;</hi> So that it is <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>Aggregato,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> make up one <hi>Body,</hi> and one <hi>Seed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There were ſeveral <hi>Promiſes</hi> made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſome concerned him alone, ſome concerned himſelf and his <hi>Seed,</hi> according to the <hi>Fleſh</hi> alone; The <hi>Gentiles</hi> had nothing to do with them: <hi>That all Nations ſhould be Bleſs'd in Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Seed;</hi> This belongs to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as well as the <hi>Jews,</hi> This is one <hi>Promiſe.</hi> But we muſt have <hi>Promiſes</hi> in the Plural Number made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> if you take away this, <hi>I will be the God of thee and thy Seed,</hi> I know not how to make the <hi>Text</hi> true.</p>
               <p>But if this be granted, then this <hi>Verſe</hi> and the fourteenth <hi>Verſe</hi> are both true; <hi>now the Bleſſing of Abraham is come upon the Gentiles through Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have inſiſted long upon this Branch,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:32571:44"/>becauſe the pinch of the Controverſie lies here, and theſe Grounds are to me ſo ſtrong, that unleſs the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> bring <hi>Texts</hi> as ſtrong as an expreſs <hi>Scripture</hi> for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, I ſhall not regard them: nor am I come yet to the <hi>Texts</hi> in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> to prove the <hi>Church-Memberſhip</hi> of <hi>Infants,</hi> though it may be inferred from ſome I have named already.</p>
               <p>The laſt Branch in the <hi>Sillogiſm</hi> is, That if this Gracious <hi>Covenant</hi> be not Repealed but ſtand firm, <hi>then it muſt be Signed, and Sealed to them who are under it;</hi> this I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe will not be denyed. The Bleſſed God makes no <hi>Covenants,</hi> but he Seals them.</p>
               <p>That the Tree of Life, and the Tree of the knowledge of Good and Evil, were <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments</hi> and <hi>Seals,</hi> belonging to the firſt <hi>Covenant,</hi> I ſee is the Opinion of very Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Godly Divines. When God makes a <hi>Covenant</hi> with <hi>Noah,</hi> and all the <hi>Creatures,</hi> God Seals it; when with <hi>Abraham,</hi> God Seals it; and though the Seal be changed, yet it hath another Seal added in the Room of it. Our weak <hi>Faith</hi> hath need of ſtrengthening, and all too little, if God's Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit doth not ſtep in.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:32571:44"/>
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p>NOw let us come to the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and hear how they prove the Repealing of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and the un-Churching of the Children of <hi>Believing Jews.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About a quarter of a year after I had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed my <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> a <hi>Neighbour</hi> brought me Mr. <hi>Edward Hutchinſon</hi> againſt <hi>Paedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pabtiſm,</hi> to read it, but it was ſent for again, ſo that I did but read his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed Congregations;</hi> and a Letter, which I think concerned Mr. <hi>Wills,</hi> and the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Book, <hi>p.</hi> 3. he ſtates the <hi>Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and proves, <hi>That the Infants of Believing Gentiles are not the Seed of Abraham; ſo that Infant Church-Memberſhip and Baptiſm falls to the Ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> But he muſt prove that the <hi>Infants</hi> of the <hi>Believing Jews,</hi> are not the <hi>Seed of Abraham,</hi> or elſe <hi>Infants Church-Memberſhip</hi> does not fall. I had reaſon to ſtate the <hi>Queſtion</hi> ſo, as to the <hi>Believing Jews;</hi> but if he will yield the <hi>Infants</hi> of <hi>Believing Jews</hi> to be <hi>Members,</hi> and have a Right to <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> I will prove the <hi>Infants</hi> of <hi>Believing Gentiles</hi> are <hi>Church-Members,</hi> and have a Right to <hi>Baptiſm. There is neither Jew nor Greek,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28. no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:32571:45"/>now but of this more hereafter.</p>
               <p>Again, we ſhall ſee whether his Arguments do not cut off the <hi>Infants</hi> of <hi>Believing Jews,</hi> as well as <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Argu.</hi> His firſt <hi>Sillogiſm, If none be the Children of Abraham, but thoſe that do the works of Abraham, then Infants are not the Seed of Abraham, but the Antecedent is true.</hi> Joh. 8.39. Therefore,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> If none be rational Creatures, but thoſe that can <hi>Sillogize,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Hutchiſon</hi> doth, then <hi>Infants</hi> are not rational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. But, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you ſay my Antecedent is falſe, ſo is yours; but it ſhews how ſtrong your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If <hi>Iſaac</hi> at eight Days old, when <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed,</hi> do not the works of his <hi>Father Abraham,</hi> then he is not <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Seed;</hi> you argue from no <hi>Doing,</hi> to no <hi>Seed.</hi> A ſtrange Argument Sir!</p>
               <p n="3">3. If any of thoſe <hi>Jews,</hi> to whom our Lord ſpake theſe words, had any Male-Children born that day, they had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Seed, Members</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and muſt be <hi>Circumciſed</hi> the eighth day, or Sin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Argu.</hi> His ſecond <hi>Sillogiſm, If thoſe who are Chriſt's are only Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Seed, then Infants are not Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Seed, but the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:32571:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>is true.</hi> Gal. 3.3.19. <hi>they are not Chriſts by Calling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Is there no way to be made Chriſt's, but by <hi>Calling?</hi> can he that made the Ear and the Heart, come no way to the Heart, but by the Ear? what Divinity is this? can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not he that infuſes the Soul into the Body, infuſe Grace into the Soul, but by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Chriſt commands little Children to be brought to him, and none to forbid them. <hi>Mark</hi> 10.13, 14. &amp;c. <hi>Of ſuch is the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> then they muſt be Chriſt's; we believe Chriſt, Sir, before you.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe <hi>Iſaac</hi> at eight days old, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not anſwer a Call of Chriſt's, therefore he is none of Chriſt's, a good Argument. Was <hi>John</hi> none of Chriſt's, when he leaped in his Mothers Womb, when <hi>Mary</hi> came to <hi>Elizabeth?</hi> Luk. 1.44.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Argu.</hi> 3. His third <hi>Sillogiſm, If none be Bleſſed with Abraham, but thoſe that are of Faith, than Infants are not the Seed of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, but the Antecedent is true.</hi> Gal. 3.9. Therefore,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Does the <hi>Text</hi> ſay <hi>Actual Faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Alas, poor <hi>Infants!</hi> by this <hi>Author</hi> ye are Curſed, no poor <hi>Infant</hi> dying an <hi>Infant,</hi> can be Bleſſed. Yea, thoſe <hi>Infants</hi> whom Chriſt Bleſſed, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.16. were Curſed though he Bleſſed them, for they could not
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:32571:46"/>Act <hi>Faith</hi> upon Chriſt. Did <hi>Iſaac</hi> when <hi>Circumciſed</hi> the eighth Day, put forth an Act of <hi>Faith</hi> upon Chriſt to come?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Believers in Chriſt are ſo, either
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Actually</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>or <hi>Siminally.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Actual</hi> Believers in Chriſt are ſo, either
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Viſibly and Really,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>or <hi>Viſibly only.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Viſibly only,</hi> ſuch were thoſe, to whom in your <hi>Preface to your Baptiſed Congregations,</hi> you thus ſpeak, <hi>they are not all Iſrael, that are of Iſrael. I know there is droſs mingled with your Silver, Chaff among your Wheat, and the</hi> Canaanite <hi>is ſtill in the Land.</hi> It ſeems then you find <hi>Droſs, Chaff, Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anites,</hi> and not true <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in your <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed Congregations;</hi> but you did look on them as <hi>viſible Believers,</hi> when you Dipped them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Seminally</hi> ſo, and they firſt; ſuch as are Reputed ſo by God's <hi>Covenant,</hi> with <hi>Believing Parents</hi> and their <hi>Seed.</hi> 2ly, Such, who beſides this Reputation, are regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Spirit, which is not without <hi>Faith Seminally.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Argu.</hi> 4. His fourth <hi>Sillogiſm, If the Children of the Fleſh are not the Children of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:32571:46"/>God, then Infants now are not the Seed of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, but the Antecedent is true.</hi> Rom. 9.8. Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I deny the Conſequence.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, It ſeems then, no <hi>Infants</hi> are the Children of God, by this Argument; a very bold and wretched Aſſertion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is a double <hi>Adoption,</hi> External, Eccleſiaſtical, and Internal, Heavenly Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, that hath a Heavenly, Eternal Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance belonging to it; they who had only the firſt, theſe were called the Children of God. <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.1. and 16. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21. to theſe pertain the <hi>Adoption.</hi> Rom. 9.4.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>Queſtion</hi> is not who are the true Children of God, that have that Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance prepared for them, but who are to be Reputed the Children of God, <hi>in foro Eccleſiaſtico,</hi> Viſibly; ſo that they are Members of a Viſible Church, and have Right to a Viſible Ordinance, in the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church. The <hi>Droſs,</hi> the <hi>Chaff,</hi> the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> the <hi>falſe Iſraelites,</hi> which you tell us, are in your <hi>Baptized Congregations,</hi> are none of the Children of God, in a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Senſe; but your <hi>Baptiſts</hi> did judge them to be Believers Actually in Chriſt, if ſo, then Children of God, then you admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them Members of your Churches, and ſo Baptized them by Dipping. They
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:32571:47"/>were looked upon as <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Seed,</hi> when you admitted them.</p>
               <p>The next thing he falls upon is, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.39. of which after.</p>
               <p>I could go no further, the Book was ſent for, nor did I intend to make any large Diſcourſe, though it had continued with me: by theſe four Arguments we have a taſte of the Man's ſtrength.</p>
               <p>By theſe Arguments, [and the next which follows, which is in all their mouths] let the <hi>Reader</hi> judge, whither they do not all ſtrike as much at the Grace and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, in his <hi>Covenanting</hi> with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and his <hi>Seed;</hi> Conſtituting the Church of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Parents, and their <hi>Seed,</hi> and Circumciſing of the <hi>Infants,</hi> as they do prove, that now the <hi>Infants</hi> ſhould not be admitted into the Goſpel-Church, nor Baptiſed. So that the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> tells God, that if he will Conſtitute the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> right, he muſt let their Children be grown up. Firſt, Learn to know the God of <hi>Abraham.</hi> Second, Put forth an Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Faith in Chriſt, the Promiſed <hi>Seed</hi> to come, as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw his Day and rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.56. Thirdly, Let them do the works of their <hi>Father Abraham. Joh.</hi> 8.39. Fourthly, Let them manifeſt that they are really the Children of God, then admit
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:32571:47"/>them Members, and Circumciſe them. Does not all their Arguments tend to this? they will teach the Holy, Wiſe God, how to Conſtitute Churches better. I will not be afraid to ſay, That all the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> that ever were, or ſhall be, ſhall never be able to caſt the <hi>Seed</hi> of Believing Parents out of the Church, by any Conſequence drawn from any <hi>Text</hi> in the <hi>Bible,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt give us clearer <hi>Texts,</hi> before we ſhall believe them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>BUt come we to the great Argument, which all uſe, and that wherewith I was aſſaulted. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. and <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>Only Believers are to be Baptiſed.</hi> To which I Anſwer,</p>
               <p>This took with me in my Meditations, I thought there was ſtrength in it.</p>
               <p>Had the <hi>Goſpel-Church</hi> been firſt erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed amongſt the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and had <hi>Baptiſm</hi> been firſt Inſtituted in the <hi>Gentile-Churches,</hi> then the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> Argument from hence, would have carryed me. But the firſt <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Church</hi> was erected among the <hi>Jews,</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> was Inſtituted in the <hi>Jewiſh-Church</hi> firſt, where the <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> cannot deny but the <hi>Infants</hi> were Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:32571:48"/>with their <hi>Parents,</hi> and under the Seal of the <hi>Covenant.</hi> So that they muſt firſt prove that by this <hi>Text,</hi> the Children of the <hi>Believing Jews</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel-Church,</hi> were not Members with their <hi>Parents,</hi> which I am ſure cannot be forced from this <hi>Text,</hi> nor doth it in the leaſt prove the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing of <hi>Abraham's Covenant</hi> with his <hi>Seed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Circumciſion</hi> did Seal up the <hi>Promiſed Seed,</hi> in whom all Nations ſhould be Bleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or <hi>Chriſt</hi> to come; and ſurely requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, therefore their <hi>Faith</hi> in the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> to come. After Chriſt's Aſcenſion, in the <hi>Goſpel-Church Baptiſm</hi> ſeals up this <hi>Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Seed,</hi> or <hi>Chriſt</hi> now come, with a full and clear Revelation of him; the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the <hi>Faith</hi> as to the Object of it, is only <hi>Chriſt</hi> to come, and come. If then the Children of the <hi>Jews,</hi> while the Parents did believe in the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> to come, were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <hi>Covenant,</hi> Reputed Members of the Church, and <hi>Circumciſed;</hi> ſhould, when their Parents believe in <hi>Chriſt</hi> come, be caſt out of <hi>Covenant,</hi> out of the Church, and not <hi>Baptiſed,</hi> I know no Reaſon, nor Warrant from God's Word; this would have made ſtrange work.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſay the <hi>Jews did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the Meſſiah to come,</hi> they muſt prove it; the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> ran much in their minds,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:32571:48"/>we may ſee by the Woman of <hi>Samaria. Joh.</hi> 4.25. Read <hi>Acts</hi> 26.7. and by the <hi>Jews. Joh.</hi> 1.19, 20, 21. If Chriſt were then clearly revealed, why ſhould this caſt the <hi>Infant</hi> out? the <hi>Infant</hi> is not therefore guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the more Sin, when Chriſt was clearly revealed, and ſo deſerve to be caſt out.</p>
               <p>We are to conſider Ordinances in their Inſtitution, wherefore God appointed them, what they carry in them, in their own Nature, and what Men ought to do who partake of them, not what Men do; we know what <hi>Baptiſm</hi> ſignifies, what it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, and what they ought to do who par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of it, though Men abuſe it. The Caſe was the ſame as to <hi>Circumciſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That this was one thing it Sealed up, as I ſaid, the <hi>Promiſe</hi> of Chriſt to come, the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> cannot deny, and it is the true An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer which <hi>Pererius</hi> gives, from <hi>Aquinus,</hi> to that <hi>Question,</hi> what was the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Circumciſion</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and of other <hi>Nations?</hi> for that other <hi>Nations</hi> did <hi>Circumciſe</hi> beſides the <hi>Jews,</hi> not only <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, de ratione Circumvis, &amp; Hierom.</hi> on <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. <hi>ult.</hi> [who upon that <hi>Text</hi> I think well;] but alſo <hi>Herodotus,</hi> who lived ſome hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of <hi>years before Chriſt</hi> in <hi>Xerxes</hi>'s Time, tells us, inſomuch, that <hi>Herodotus</hi> ſaith the <hi>Jews</hi> took it up from the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> among
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:32571:49"/>whom it was in ſo much eſteem, that there was no entrance into the moſt Honourable Offices amongſt them, unleſs they were <hi>Circumciſed.</hi> Now <hi>Pererius</hi> makes this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference: <hi>Other Nations uſed it, taking it up as a cuſtom and right, tranſmitted to them from their fore-Fathers, whom they had in Honour. But the</hi> Jews <hi>uſed it, as it was a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament containing in it, the Profeſſion of their Faith and Obedience towards God, and the Divine Promiſe of the</hi> Meſſiah <hi>to come;</hi> he adds, <hi>And Expiation of Original Sin,</hi> as the Ancients ſpeak of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and ſo many do now.</p>
               <p>That other <hi>Nations</hi> do not uſe it as a Seal of God's <hi>Covenant,</hi> it appears by the time of <hi>Circumciſing;</hi> the day God appointed, was the eigth day, but <hi>Iſhmael's</hi> Poſterity, <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe</hi> in the thirteenth year of their Age, then <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was <hi>Circumciſed;</hi> ſo that it is meerly in Honour of him, ſo <hi>Joſephus</hi> tells us. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>To go on, If then the <hi>Seed</hi> of the <hi>Jews</hi> believing in Chriſt come, be ſtill under the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and <hi>Church-Members</hi> with their Parents, and if ſo, ought to be Baptiſed, by Mr. <hi>Tombe</hi>'s Conceſſion; Then let the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Gentiles</hi> and their <hi>Seed</hi> come in alſo for now no difference between <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Greek, Gal.</hi> 3.28. And for more full proof,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:32571:49"/>the Apoſtle tells the <hi>believing Epheſians,</hi> and ſo all <hi>believing Gentiles,</hi> Epheſ. 2.19. <hi>We are no more ſtrangers</hi> [<hi>from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of Iſrael,</hi> v. 12.] but Chriſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving broken down the middle Wall of Partition between the <hi>Jews</hi> and us, v. 14.] <hi>we are now fellow-citizens with the Saints, and of the Houſhold of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the word <hi>Fellow-citizens,</hi> in the City or Church of the <hi>Jews:</hi> I pray, who were eſteemed <hi>Citizens?</hi> Were not the Children put into <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Charter: were not they then Citizens with their Parents? What, hath God ſent his <hi>Quo Warranto,</hi> and taken away <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Charter, when the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, the Citizens, believe in Chriſt ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and keep Covenant with him, and walk in the ſteps of <hi>Abraham:</hi> will now God take away their Charter, and caſt out their Seed from being Citizens? What, <hi>hath Chriſt by his blood made us both One, taking down the partition-wall between</hi> Jew <hi>and</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, <hi>v.</hi> 14. And doth he now ſet up the <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition Wall</hi> between the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> believing Parent and his Seed, bringing now the Seed of the believing <hi>Jews</hi> into that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition the <hi>Gentiles</hi> were in before Chriſt came, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.11, 12. Shall the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> make us believe this, unleſs God hath ſaid ſo in expreſs terms? What a Bar had this
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:32571:50"/>been againſt the <hi>Jews</hi> ever receiving the Goſpel: Did they any where make this Objection againſt it? Now we <hi>Gentiles</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, are <hi>Fellow-citizens</hi> with them of the ſame <hi>Houſhold of God</hi> with them. Are not Children part of the <hi>Houſhold?</hi> Were not the <hi>Jews</hi> Children part of the <hi>Houſhold of God?</hi> then the Apoſtle tells us, we alſo are Fellow-citizens, and of the Houſhold of God, as the <hi>Jews</hi> are.</p>
               <p>As for the Texts, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. and <hi>Mark</hi> 16. Bleſſed Jeſus, the Promiſed Seed to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> in whom all Nations ſhould be bleſſed, is now come; fulfilled the Law, Crucified, Dead, Aſcended: Salvation is onely to be had in him. Now this was the <hi>great Doctrine</hi> the Apoſtles were to preach, firſt to the <hi>Jews,</hi> than to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and call all Nations to believe in this Chriſt, that they may be <hi>bleſſed,</hi> according to the Promiſe made to <hi>Abraham.</hi> True, none but Adult perſons, or perſons of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, can underſtand this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and actually believe in Chriſt. No more could any but <hi>Jews</hi> Adult, or of ripe years, underſtand the Promiſe of Chriſt <hi>to come,</hi> in whom all Nations ſhould be bleſſed; but yet the <hi>Jews</hi> Children were reputed with them Believers in the <hi>Meſſiah to come,</hi> by Gods Covenant with them, and the Church
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:32571:50"/>Conſtituted of them. So now Believers in Chriſt come, their <hi>Seed</hi> are Reputed with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Muſculus</hi> [whom my <hi>Author</hi> hath put in his Catalogue of <hi>Authors, [hoc. com.</hi> p. 603.] which makes the ignorant <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> think he is on their ſide; but rancks the <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> in a ſecond, or lower degree of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> for denying <hi>Infant-baptiſm,</hi> and an <hi>Oath.</hi>] In anſwer to an Argument of the <hi>Anabaptiſts, there was a Command for Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſing, but no expreſs Command for Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</hi> Thus writes, <hi>Facit hoc non contra nos, ſed pro nobis,</hi> &amp;c. [<hi>ibid.</hi> 338.] This doth not make againſt us, but for us, ſaith he, the ſum of his anſwer [being too long to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe all] is this. <q rend="margQuotes">Since God hath plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared his Will, that the Infants of Believers, whoſe <hi>Father Abraham</hi> is, ſhould be Partakers of the Grace and Sign of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and no where do we read that this Will of God is Repealed; what neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity is there, after ſuch a clear expreſſion of his Will, to deſire another Command in the <hi>New Teſtament?</hi> Since therefore Chriſt gave no ſpecial Command, what ſhould be done with the Infants of Believers, he did ſufficiently intimate to his Apoſtles, who were <hi>Jews,</hi> and brought up among the <hi>Jews,</hi> that he did not take away that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:32571:51"/>Grace, by which God declared himſelf to be the God, not only of Believers, but alſo of their <hi>Seed,</hi> and that he will have them Sealed with the Sign of his Grace. To which, do but add, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.13, 14, 15. we may ſee Chriſt hath not taken away this Grace from them.</q> This An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of <hi>Muſculus,</hi> is full and clear, and runs upon that I have been calling for, an Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible proof of God's Repealing of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Covenant.</hi> I have rather wronged <hi>Muſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> by not Tranſcribing the whole <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph,</hi> for brevities ſake, I deſire the <hi>Reader</hi> to view him. For my part, I do not yet ſee any abſurdity, if I ſhould ſay, as in the fourth Commandment, the morality of it being, that a ſeventh part of time be ſet a part for the Worſhip of God; therefore let God pleaſe to change the day, yet that Commandment binds us to ſanctify that day. So when God ſhall pleaſe to make a Gracious <hi>Covenant</hi> with Believing <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his <hi>Seed,</hi> and gives Command to have that <hi>Covenant</hi> Sealed, and never declares his Repealing of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and its Seal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; the <hi>Covenant</hi> ſtanding ſtill in force, though God may pleaſe to change the Seal, and bring in another Seal under a new diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, yet God's former Command may well warrant us to adminiſter the Sign
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:32571:51"/>and Seal of the <hi>Covenant</hi> to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Seed,</hi> as before.</p>
               <p>Sure I am, this expreſs Command the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> require for Baptiſing <hi>Infants,</hi> will caſt out the <hi>Lord's-Day,</hi> and <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> out of a Chriſtian Common-wealth, <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men from the Lord's Table;</hi> For though there were divers Women attended Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.2, 3. yet there was not one of them with him at his Inſtitution of the <hi>Lord</hi>'s <hi>Supper:</hi> nor do we read expreſly, that Women were at the <hi>Lord</hi>'s <hi>Table</hi> in their Churches; For him that would prove it from the words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, there tell us, That <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is of the <hi>Epiceen Gender,</hi> and includes <hi>Male</hi> and <hi>Female.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, If <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> did alwaies ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy <hi>Male</hi> and <hi>Female,</hi> and not the <hi>Male</hi> only, then it were a good proof: but I told twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty places in <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Goſpel [I looked no further] where it ſignifies only the <hi>Male.</hi> Beſides, what <hi>Gender</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of, which is joyned with it? Nor can we have ground to Excommunicate Women, if they walk impenitently ſcandalous in the Church.</p>
               <p>Partly upon their Principle, who call for expreſs Command, and partly becauſe the caſting out of the <hi>Seed</hi> of Believers, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing the <hi>Covenant,</hi> are ſo ſtrange, that it cannot be proved by any Conſequence I
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:32571:52"/>have yet met with, therefore I call for Srciptures as clear at leaſt as expreſs Commands, or ſignification of God's Will.</p>
               <p>To return to <hi>Infants,</hi> They muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, and have <hi>Faith</hi> ſome way, elſe they muſt all periſh; what ſhould make the thing ſo impoiſible they ſhould have the <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit</hi> or <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> and of all <hi>ſaving Graces</hi> in them? I hope it is not becauſe Chriſt is known only by Revelation. I pray, what Act of <hi>Faith</hi> in God, what Act of <hi>Love</hi> to God, or <hi>Fear</hi> of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> did <hi>Iſaach</hi> or <hi>John</hi> put forth towards God, when, being <hi>Infants</hi> they were <hi>Circumciſed?</hi> yet I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident they had the <hi>Seeds</hi> of all theſe at that time they were ſanctified then, and why not then a <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> in Chriſt? had not <hi>John</hi> it when he leaped? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt <hi>Synod</hi> held in <hi>New-England,</hi> this was one queſtion diſcuſſed; <hi>Whether we be juſtified by the Habit, or the Act of Faith?</hi> Arguments were brought <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> ſome were for the <hi>Habit</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> then why not <hi>Infants</hi> juſtified by a <hi>Habit</hi> of <hi>Faith?</hi> Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> in his proofs for <hi>Infant-baptiſm,</hi> makes this his firſt Argument; <hi>That in the very beginning of Regeneration, the Soul is a meer paſſive, the Infant is as capable of a paſſive re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of Chriſt and Grace, as another Man:
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:32571:52"/>but Baptiſm Seals to our Regeneration. [modul. theal. c.</hi> 4. <hi>th.</hi> 12. <hi>Got. of grace, p.</hi> 27. &amp;c. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cin. pro. flig. p.</hi> 781.]</p>
               <p>That ſervant of Chriſt Mr. <hi>Tho. Hooker,</hi> proves that Children may have <hi>Faith,</hi> and hath a pretty large diſcourſe upon it; The <hi>Socinians</hi> ſay it is a Dream [if they mean <hi>Actual Faith,</hi> who do not ſay it] <hi>Caelonius</hi> in anſwer to them, proves by ten or eleven Arguments, that Children may have <hi>Faith,</hi> to be ſure, we may obſerve that they whom the <hi>Holy Page</hi> Records to be Godly [except <hi>Menaſſeh</hi>] were ſo from their Child-hood. <hi>Iſaac, Jacob, Samuel, Hezekiah, Joſiah, David, Obadiah, Jehoſhaphat,</hi> where do you read of the Saints firſt running a courſe of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and then Converted? How many Children may we obſerve, that we may ſay as Dr. <hi>Thomas Goodwin</hi> ſaid, are ſanctified from the Womb. What is the matter then, that all <hi>Infants</hi> are caſt out of the Church, and muſt not be Baptiſed?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> If you ſay, <hi>If you could tell which they are, they ſhould be Baptiſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Can you tell who have <hi>ſaving-Faith</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> though they make Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Profeſſion, and tell you they have it? they who you ſay are <hi>Droſs, Chaff, Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anites,</hi> no true <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in your <hi>Baptiſed Congregations,</hi> they told you they had <hi>Faith,</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:32571:53"/>when you Dipped them, but you were mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If that be yielded, that <hi>Infants</hi> may be Regenerate, may have <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Grace Seminally,</hi> then this <hi>Text</hi> which you do ſo talk of does not cut them off from Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Covenant,</hi> let the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents be viſible Believers, by their compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent knowledg of Chriſt, profeſſion of their <hi>Faith</hi> in him, and Converſation in ſome meaſure becoming Chriſtians, giving up themſelves to the Ordinances, and Rules of Chriſt's Houſe, prove themſelves thus to be viſible Chriſtians: and we can as regularly Baptiſe the Children of ſuch Believers, as you Baptiſe your Adult perſons, though as to the reality of <hi>ſaving Faith,</hi> we are miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and ſo are you.</p>
               <p>Once more take the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. as Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> ſaith it ought to be Tranſlated, <hi>Diſciple ye all Nations,</hi> or make <hi>Diſciples.</hi> Hence the Argument.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All they that are Diſciples ought to be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the Children of Believing Parents are Diſciples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore the Children of Believing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ought to be Baptiſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Argument I gave to him who op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:32571:53"/>me, but he could not tell which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to deny; a fit Man to diſpute in a Congregation.</p>
               <p>For the proof of the Argument.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Major,</hi> is the plain <hi>Text,</hi> there is no oppoſing of that.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Minor,</hi> that ſuch Children are Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, our Divines have ſo cleared it from <hi>Acts</hi> 15.1. and 10. <hi>v.</hi> compared, and other <hi>Texts,</hi> that I will not ſay what they have ſaid before.</p>
               <p>I give my thoughts thus, They are Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</p>
               <p n="1">1ſt. By God's Reputation he eſteems them ſo; they are mine ſaith God, born to me. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.20, 21.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, They are ſo by their Parents <hi>Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of them to Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly, They are ſo by their Parents <hi>Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of them <hi>for</hi> Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4ly, They are ſo, as I may ſay, <hi>jure Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> or rather <hi>jure Religionum,</hi> all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, all Religions, take their Children to be the ſame that the Parents are.</p>
               <p>Did not the <hi>Jews</hi> take their Children to be <hi>Moſes</hi>'s <hi>Diſciples,</hi> as well as themſelves? <hi>John</hi> 9.28.</p>
               <p>Do not the <hi>Turks</hi> take their Children to be <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s <hi>Diſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les,</hi> as well as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves?
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:32571:54"/>Should you deny it, you ſhould hear of it, if not feel it.</p>
               <p>Yea, go the <hi>Indians</hi> whoſe Religion [i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I may call it ſo] is very Deviliſh and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, were it not too good a word. When the <hi>Engliſh</hi> firſt began to dwell in <hi>New-England, Maſſaſoit</hi> the <hi>Sachem</hi> of <hi>Mount Hope,</hi> made a League with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at <hi>Plymouth</hi> to live in Amity with them; The Articles were <hi>Seven;</hi> he kept the League well: A little before his death, he comes to renew his League for himſelf and his two Sons, <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Philip,</hi> this was on <hi>September</hi> 25, 1630. But in his Treatiſe he urged this, That the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhould engage never to attempt to draw any of his people to the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: he inſiſted upon it very much; but the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were reſolute, and would make no League upon ſuch terms. But this we ſee by this <hi>Heathen,</hi> that he would have his Poſterity to be reckoned as he was, though his Religion was Deviliſh.</p>
               <p>If then the Children of <hi>Jews, Turks, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans</hi> be reckoned with the Parents, why muſt not the Children of Believers in Chriſt be reckoned Diſciples of Chriſt with their Parents.</p>
               <p>The Reader I ſuppoſe will pardon me,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:32571:54"/>though I make a little Digreſſion: The Wars between the <hi>Indians</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> I ſuppoſe muſt have heard. This <hi>Philip</hi> the Son of <hi>Maſſaſoit,</hi> before-mentioned, was he that began the Wars with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> 1675. which laſted till 1677. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> when they ſaw <hi>Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoit</hi> ſtand ſo upon that <hi>Article,</hi> then ſaid, <hi>That God would root out the Poſterity of that</hi> Maſſaſoit; and ſo now it is come to paſs.</p>
               <p>That Story which my worthy Friend Mr. <hi>William Hubbard</hi> gives us of <hi>Paſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naway,</hi> [the moſt noted <hi>Paneaw</hi> or <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerer;</hi> and I believe the oldeſt man in the Country. When I ſaw him, he was reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned one of the oldeſt men of the <hi>Indians,</hi> but I perceived by the time of his dying, he lived about thirty years after] is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the obſerving. About <hi>Merimach</hi> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <hi>Anno</hi> 1660, ſeveral <hi>Sagamoors</hi> meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together, there was a great Dance: Theſe Solemnities, are the Times when the moſt Ancient tell Stories, and tranſmit them to their Poſterity. <hi>Paſſalonaway</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent made his laſt Speech, and took his Farewel: thus,</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">I am ready to die, and not likely ever to ſee you meet any more; I will now leave this word of Councel with you;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:32571:55"/>That you take heed how you quarrel with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> for though you may do them much miſchief, yet aſſuredly you will all be deſtroyed and rooted out of the Earth if you do; for I was as much an Enemy to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at their firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into theſe Parts, as any one what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, and did try all waies and means poſſible to have deſtroyed them, at leaſt to have prevented their ſitting down here, but I could no way effect it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I adviſe you never to contend with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> nor make War with them. Accordingly his eldeſt Son <hi>Wonnalancot,</hi> as ſoon as he perceived the <hi>Indians</hi> were up in Arms, he withdrew himſelf into ſome remote place, that he might not be hurt by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> or their Enemies.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <p>TO return to my <hi>Author:</hi> His <hi>Sixth</hi> Queſtion is, <hi>Whether Baptiſm did ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the room and uſe of Circumciſion?</hi> He ſaith, <hi>By no means.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Body of our Learned and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Divines ſay, <hi>It doth,</hi> and our Divines
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:32571:55"/>have ſpoken to it ſo often, that I am loath to ſay any thing to it. Shortly my thoughts were theſe:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Circumciſion</hi> came in upon <hi>Faith: Abraham</hi> believed, then he was Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed: And ſo doth <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Circumciſion did <hi>ſign Chriſt to come in the fleſh.</hi> So ſaith my Author; and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm <hi>ſigns he is come in the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Circumciſion did ſignifie [you may ſay Seal] the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Faith:</hi> So doth <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Circumciſion</hi> ſignified <hi>Sanctification:</hi> ſo do <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Circumciſion ſignified and ſealed the <hi>Covenant</hi> between <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> Gen. 17.7, 8, 9, 10, 11. So doth <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Circumciſion</hi> did oblige <hi>Iſrael</hi> to walk with God: ſo <hi>Baptiſm</hi> obligeth us.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Circumciſion</hi> did diſtinguiſh <hi>Iſrael</hi> from other Nations: ſo <hi>Baptiſm</hi> diſtinguiſheth us.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:32571:56"/>
               <p>Circumciſion reſpecting Chriſt <hi>to come,</hi> and Baptiſm <hi>Chriſt come.</hi> Hence the <hi>Jews</hi> though circumciſed, yet coming under a new Diſpenſation, ought to be baptized: much more reaſon for this, than for <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> who being a Diſciple, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.1. no queſtion was baptized, and yet after that circumciſed by <hi>Paul,</hi> v. 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Circumciſion</hi> (ſaith my Author) <hi>was to be a Bond and Obligation to keep the whole Law of</hi> Moſes: <hi>but Baptiſm is contrary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. For the Moral Law, the Rule of our Obedience, Baptiſm doth not ſolve us from that, but bind us to it: for <hi>Sanctification</hi> is held forth in our <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. As for the <hi>Ceremonial Law</hi> where <hi>Christ</hi> was ſet forth in <hi>ſhadows,</hi> no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, though when Chriſt is come, and the ſhadow's gone, that <hi>Baptiſm</hi> was contrary to it. <hi>Evangelium relatum &amp; Revelatum.</hi> But what doth this hurt us?</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Paul</hi> did not Circumciſe <hi>Timothy,</hi> with that reſpect to <hi>Circumciſion;</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> did. The <hi>Jews</hi> did look to be <hi>juſtified</hi> by the obſervation of the <hi>moral</hi> and <hi>ceremonial
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:32571:56"/>Law</hi> both, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.3. the 4th <hi>verſe</hi> unties the knot. The falſe Apoſtles urged Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.1. according to the <hi>Law of Moſes.</hi> [But Circumciſion is not of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but the Fathers, ſaith our Lord, <hi>John</hi> 7.22.] <hi>If you Circumciſe thus, and ſeek Juſtification thus, you are fallen from grace,</hi> Gal. 5.4.</p>
               <p>My Author goes on; <hi>Circumciſion ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated the carnal Seed into a carnal Church, and gave them right to carnal Ordinances: But Baptiſm was to give the ſpiritual Seed an orderly entrance into the ſpiritual Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Theſe Carnal Ordinances had their Spiritual ſignifications as well as ours.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Element in Baptiſm, <hi>Water;</hi> do but <hi>waſh the fleſh,</hi> and may be ſaid to be Carnal too in ſome ſenſe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There was a Spiritual Seed admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alſo into that Church by Circumciſion, as well as now by Baptiſm, how many Saints were in that Church?</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Chaff, Droſs, Canaanites</hi> are no Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Seed, yet ſuch have been admitted into your Spiritual Church, by <hi>Dipping.</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:32571:57"/>Mr. <hi>Hutcheſon</hi> writes true and can teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Define a Church, and you ſhall find all the Cauſes in that Church [a differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence only between a Church, and <hi>ſuch a Church</hi>] take it in the ſtricteſt notion. 1. The <hi>efficient</hi> Cauſe is <hi>God,</hi> that is here. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.6. <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.21. 3ly, The <hi>formal</hi> Cauſe joyned in Covenant, with God and one with another, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.12. <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.10, 14. <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.8. [Beſides their Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion.] This ſome Brethren make the <hi>form</hi> of a Church: here it is. 4ly, <hi>Final</hi> Cauſe, To walk with God, and keep his Ordinances: it was here, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.7. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath ſpoken ſo much to this, that I ſay no more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Women were not circumciſed,</hi> ſaith my Author.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> No, how could they? 1. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle gives you an anſwer, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3. 2ly, <hi>Rivet</hi> ſaith well; <hi>Sed quia in viris acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, ut loquuntur, generationis &amp; propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis hominum eſt principium, quo tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt corruptionem in poſteros, ſignum ideo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuit in praecipuo ſexu, ita tamen, ut foemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae viris annexae &amp; in iis cenſerentur, qui fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliorum capitae debebant eſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:32571:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>For <hi>Acts</hi> 38.39. which my Author op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth, and brings in Biſhop <hi>Taylor,</hi> [a man croſs to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in point of Original Sin.] And Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> on his ſide, telling us, It is an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncludent Argument to infer Baptiſm from hence. [I do not wonder that</hi> Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts <hi>make ſo much uſe of Dr.</hi> Taylor.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> With the Biſhop's favour, there is a difference between theſe two Phraſes, The <hi>Children of Iſrael,</hi> and this; <hi>You and your children.</hi> Here is a Copulative Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction which is not there. They were the wounded Perſons to whom <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks, that asked him a <hi>queſtion,</hi> but their Children did not ask, nor were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with them moſt likely.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Notandi autem, &amp;c. But the three degrees are to be noted, to whom the Promiſe is made,</hi> 1. <hi>To the</hi> Jews. 2. <hi>To their Children.</hi> 3. <hi>To the</hi> Gentiles.</p>
               <p>As for Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> though I honour him much for his great Learning one way, yet I think as to an Argument, whether it be Concludent or not, other men may know as well as he. <hi>Voſſius, Rivet, Calvin, Gerhard, Aretius,</hi> and the <hi>Aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines,</hi> [though ſlighted by him] do all conclude <hi>Infant-baptiſm</hi> from hence; they
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:32571:58"/>could judge of a Concludent Argument.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What this <hi>Promiſe</hi> is, I ſee there are very different Apprehenſions. Some take it to be that in <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. So Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> and divers others. The <hi>Dutch</hi> ſay, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. &amp; <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. <hi>Ahapide</hi> ſaith, The <hi>Promiſed Seed in whom all Nations ſhould be bleſſed.</hi> Thus <hi>Aretius,</hi> The <hi>Promiſe of the</hi> Meſſiah, <hi>and the benefits that come by him, made to</hi> Abraham <hi>and his Seed,</hi> Gen. 13. To which the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4. hath a reſpect, <hi>the Promiſes belong to them.</hi> Thus <hi>Aretius,</hi> and <hi>Horino</hi> inclines this way.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, whatever the <hi>Promiſe</hi> be, it was that which the <hi>Jews</hi> and their Children were now under, [<hi>For to you do the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of that Promiſe appertain if you will lay hold of it,</hi> ſaith Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> on Text.] The Promiſe did appertain to them, both Parents and Children, but not to the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> as yet till they be called.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly, That <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is a general word I grant, ſeven or eight times uſed for little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the <hi>New Teſtament. Fit mentitio li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berorum</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſine diſcretione aetatis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Voſſius.</hi> Let your Children be little or great, to your Children the Promiſe doth
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:32571:58"/>belong, as well as to you. <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.25. <hi>His Blood be upon us,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>and upon your Children;</hi> were not there the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren diſtinct from the Parents? and do not Children there ſignify their little ones, their poſterity, of what Age ſoever? would Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Taylor</hi> deny it? and 'tis probable that God brought this Imprecation to mind, and <hi>Peter</hi> may aim at that.</p>
               <p>Be the promiſe what it will then, I would try for one Argument from hence.</p>
               <p>They that are <hi>Church-Members</hi> ought to be Baptiſed.</p>
               <p>But Children of Believing Parents are <hi>Church-Members.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore, they ought to be Baptiſed.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Major,</hi> the <hi>Doctor,</hi> nor any elſe will deny.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Minor,</hi> I prove thus.</p>
               <p>They to whom <hi>Promiſes</hi> do appertain, they are <hi>Church-Members.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to the Children of Believing Parents <hi>Promiſes</hi> do appertain. Therefore,</p>
               <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is plain, no <hi>Promiſe</hi> belong to any perſon out of the <hi>Viſible Church.</hi> Epheſ. 2.12. while the <hi>Epheſians</hi> were out of the <hi>Viſible Church, they were Strangers from the Covenants of Promiſe.</hi> Rom. 9.4. the <hi>Promiſe</hi> did belong to the <hi>Jews,</hi> not to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:32571:59"/>us <hi>Gentiles,</hi> till grafted into <hi>Abraham</hi>'s ſtock.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is proud from the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>The Promiſe is to you, and your Children,</hi> we are under the outward diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation now; you nor your Children ſhall loſe your Title to it, by Repenting and Believing, but then you ſhall feel the ſaving benefit added to pour outward Title. Again,</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Will you reſtrain the promiſe to the gift of the Spirit, as the Verſe before; Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> moves the Queſtion? what kind of gifts theſe were, inward or outward, for both theſe are promiſed indefinitely to Believers. <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.38, 39. there the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward gifts, enabling humble ſincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, for the Duties of a Chriſtian Life, called, <hi>The Renewing of the Holy Ghoſt. Tit.</hi> 3.5. joyned to the <hi>Laver</hi> of Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; he concludes 'tis beſt to comprehend both.</q> Thus Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> on the <hi>Text.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let me add, If the Spirit be here meant, it muſt be ſo underſtood, that it may be the benefit of as many as ever God ſhall call to the Worlds End, be they never ſo many Millions; the words <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> will force it. The <hi>Promiſe</hi> is to <hi>All,</hi> as many, be they never ſo many, if called. There are <hi>many called, few choſen,</hi> but if called, there is an
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:32571:59"/>outward Title to it, and to their Children, elſe the Sentence is not full; and I proved before we are fellow-Citizens of the ſame houſhold, grafted <hi>into the ſame ſtock, Jew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> all one: The <hi>Jews</hi> and their Children were under it, when not effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called. <hi>The Promiſe is to you and your Children,</hi> now they were Children of the <hi>Covenant. Act.</hi> 3.25. nor can there be any reaſon given, why the Children of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Gentile</hi> ſhould not be included, and meant here, as well as of the <hi>Jews.</hi> Hence, ſince the <hi>Doctor</hi> thus interprets the <hi>Promiſe</hi> of the <hi>Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They to whom the <hi>Promiſe</hi> of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing <hi>Spirit</hi> doth belong, they may be Baptiſed.</p>
               <p>But to the Children of Believing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, the <hi>Promiſe</hi> of the renewing <hi>Spirit</hi> doth belong, as it did to the <hi>Jews.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Children of Believing Parents may be Baptiſed.</p>
               <p>That there can be Regeneration without the Spirit, no Chriſtian will affirm. That there can be a Heavenly Inheritance with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Regeneration the Scripture denies. That the Spirit of God cannot Regenerate an <hi>Infant,</hi> he muſt be a ſtrange Chriſtian, [if any at all] who dares ſay it. If <hi>John</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:32571:60"/>was filled with the <hi>Spirit,</hi> from his Mothers Womb, God can give his Spirit to other <hi>Infants,</hi> though in a leſs meaſure.</p>
               <p>As to the <hi>Text</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. that <hi>Text</hi> hath been ſo cleared by our Divines, that I wonder my <hi>Author</hi> ſhould not be fatisfied, but to come up with his <hi>Ligitimacy,</hi> as if that were the ſenſe of <hi>Children being Holy.</hi> When as</p>
               <p n="1">1ſt. The Apoſtle is not writing to a <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthian Husband,</hi> that had two Wives, but only one Wife; as 12, 13, 14. <hi>v.</hi> ſo that if that <hi>Text, Mat.</hi> 2.15. could be brought to prove a Matrimonial-Holineſs, then they were Holy, and Children Holy, before the Goſpel came; but this is a Holineſs ariſing from one of the Parents, being a Believer: Beſides, <hi>Joſeph, Benjamin, Solomon,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others, were never called <hi>Baſtards,</hi> or thought to be ſo, though <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>David</hi> had more Wives then one.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, Then all the Children in <hi>Corinth,</hi> though the Parents were lawfully Marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, were <hi>Baſtards,</hi> before the Goſpel came.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly, When then the Apoſtle writes to the Saints in <hi>Corinth.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1, 2. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.1. the meaning is, <hi>to you that are Legitimate, and not Baſtards in Corinth.</hi> What difference between <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> there, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> here? Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:32571:60"/>do your examples from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> help you at all.</p>
               <p>For 1ſt. By an <hi>Antiphraſis,</hi> or <hi>Euphemiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> the words ſignifies the quite contrary, <hi>Bleſs,</hi> and <hi>Curſe, Holy,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean;</hi> [or <hi>Sodomite,</hi> as we Tranſlate.]</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, The words are ſo uſed in an oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite ſenſe, in ſeveral other <hi>Scriptures,</hi> that prove one another.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly, The ſenſe of the <hi>Text</hi> forces us ſo to render their ſignification.</p>
               <p n="1">1. But then you muſt Tranſlate <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> by ſome word which is quite contrary to <hi>Holineſs,</hi> ſo that one expel the other: <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traria ſunt pellentis naturae,</hi> but <hi>Legitimacy</hi> and <hi>Holineſs</hi> are not contraries in reſpect of this Subject, for he may be <hi>Legitimate</hi> and <hi>Holy</hi> too, I know: you muſt then read <hi>elſe were your Children unclean, but now they are unclean.</hi> This is good Senſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As the word <hi>Holy,</hi> is never taken in the <hi>Holy Page</hi> for <hi>Legitamacy,</hi> nor can you juſtify it by any <hi>Text,</hi> as we can the former, clearly by ſeveral <hi>Texts.</hi> A <hi>Seed</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God's Inſtitution in Marriage, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his appointment, Ordination in <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.15. and the <hi>Holy Seed. Ezra.</hi> 9.2. differ very much: beſides, as I ſaid, the Children of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were <hi>Holy,</hi> if
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:32571:61"/>that were the Senſe before the Goſpel came.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Nor is there the leaſt preſſing neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty why it ſhould not be taken, as in the <hi>Scriptures</hi> I mention. Nay, there is a pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neceſſity to force that it cannot be meant <hi>Legitimacy,</hi> becauſe it follows upon the <hi>Faith</hi> of one Parent, which <hi>Legitimacy</hi> doth not.</p>
               <p>For <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which you ſay alwaies ſignifies <hi>Authority,</hi> yet 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.15. [I ſuppoſe you mean the tenth] it ſignifies a <hi>Vail.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Who tranſlated the word ſo? I have viewed nine <hi>Tranſlators,</hi> and they render it <hi>Power</hi> as we do. <hi>A Metonimy</hi> of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, we know there is the meaning being, a covering in ſign that ſhe is under the <hi>Authority</hi> of her Husband. <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.65. A Phraſe whereby the thing ſignified is aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to the Sign, the propriety of the word is here meant and intended; that ſhe ſhew her ſelf to be under <hi>Authority.</hi> The <hi>Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiopick</hi> Tranſlation, to give the Senſe, turn the <hi>Subſtantive</hi> into a <hi>Verb;</hi> but hower, this doth not at all ſuit your deſign. In the word <hi>Holy,</hi> here is no <hi>Metonimy, Sign,</hi> or thing ſignified.</p>
               <p>I ſee nothing of moment more to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>and I doubt not my Author hath been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter anſwered by others, though I ſaw none, till I had done.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:32571:61"/>
               <head>SECT. VII.</head>
               <p>THen my <hi>Author</hi> proceeds to the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Baptiſing, and tells us what <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifies; quotes <hi>Biſhop Taylor, Doctor Hammond,</hi> and many that ſay it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies <hi>Immerſion;</hi> and who is ſo ignorant, that knows not this? but is my <hi>Author</hi> ſo knowing, that he can prove it ſignifies only <hi>Immerſion,</hi> or dowzing a perſon over head and cars? did <hi>Biſhop Taylor,</hi> and <hi>Doctor Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> Baptiſe ſo, and only ſo? let him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. Why did not my <hi>Author</hi> prove that the word ſignifies only ſo, in <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2. [ſomething you would ſay to this, but 'tis pittyful] <hi>Mark</hi> 7.4. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.38. the <hi>Phariſee</hi> marvelled that Chriſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> had not firſt Baptiſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Dinner; How the <hi>Jews</hi> uſe to waſh hands, you may gueſs, by 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.11. when <hi>Eliſha</hi> waited on <hi>Elijah; He powred water on the hands of Elijah,</hi> did not <hi>Elijah</hi> then Baptiſe, or waſh his hands? was not the <hi>Baſon</hi> and <hi>Ewer,</hi> and the little <hi>Ciſterns</hi> with Water, common in <hi>England,</hi> and in ſome places ſtill to this day? and do we not
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:32571:62"/>waſh by letting of Water run upon our hands, or powring upon them.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> is ſignified you tell us; and threetimes Baptiſing with the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost,</hi> is expreſſed by powering of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What our <hi>Authors</hi> have ſaid about their practice in hotter Countries, where Baptiſm was firſt Inſtituted, you know; there they did commonly waſh, you were bound by the Law to waſh. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.4. with <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit.</hi> 15.19. and 18, 19. So <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.5. but in our cold Climates, this is not ſo common.</p>
               <p>However, to me it ſeems ſtrange, that there ſhould be ſo much ſtreſs put upon Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and ſo much upon the manner of Baptiſing, as the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> lay, and yet the <hi>Holy Page</hi> hath not Recorded how it ſhould be performed. To Baptiſe an <hi>Infant,</hi> I could do as Mr. <hi>Chancy</hi> did in <hi>New-England,</hi> and as of old they did in <hi>England;</hi> as an Antient Gentleman, of good quality in <hi>Suffolk</hi> told me, <hi>He remembred the practice, by a good token, One Infant was ſo fowled with its green Excrement, when it came to be Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped,</hi> [a handſome ſight in a Congregation, when we are about Holy Things] that he could not forget it; but how to Baptiſe an
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:32571:62"/>
                  <hi>Adult</hi> perſon, and heavy Body, I cannot tell. If they go into the Water, into the Element, they Baptiſe themſelves ſo far as their body is in the Water; The <hi>Baptiſt</hi> doth not Dip that part.</p>
               <p>As for their Clothes, I hope they do not go in with them, to Baptiſe, or Waſh them. certainly there ought to be an immediate Aplication of the Sign, [the Water] to the Body; that our Baptiſm hath a reference to the <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.4. I ſee ſeveral Men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, and have ſhown us how this Cuſtom of Waſhing new born Babes was derived almoſt to all Nations, but neither then, nor now do our Women put on a Shirt, or any thing upon the <hi>Infant,</hi> and then waſh it, but they apply the Water immediately to the Body; I am ſure it ſhould be ſo in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. <hi>Voſſius</hi> gives us large <hi>Teſtimonies</hi> out of Antient Writers, how that <hi>Men, Women,</hi> and <hi>Children,</hi> in thoſe Countries, were all Baptiſed. [<hi>De Baptis. p.</hi> 350.] [I wonder the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſhould be ſo angry with Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>] becauſe he ſaith they Baptiſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, the <hi>Women</hi> only had a little covering before them, (yea they had a Myſtery in the pulling off their Clothes, to ſhew their pulling off the <hi>Old Man,</hi> ſome where I have read,) after their Dipping, they were An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:32571:63"/>When a tumult aroſe in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty about <hi>Chryſolſtom,</hi> how the <hi>Women</hi> that were about Baptiſing, ran away naked; with other things there we may read.</p>
               <p>Certainly God's Inſtitutions are ſuch, that we may Celebrate them at Noon-day, before all Men, let them be Spectators; and if this muſt be the way, let them Baptiſe for me, and Annoint too if they pleaſe.</p>
               <p>So that <hi>Modeſty</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> be preſerved, I am of <hi>Cyrian's,</hi> and <hi>Auſtin's</hi> mind in this Point, who left it indifferent, ſo you do not abſolutely tye us up to one, and deny all Baptiſm by Dipping. [<hi>Cypr.</hi> 249. <hi>Auſt.</hi> 10.3. <hi>p.</hi> 207.]</p>
               <p>Other Divines have anſwered this more fully, and therefore I break off.</p>
               <p>Here a Queſtion falls in, which I never did ſo much as think of, till now I ſay Mr. <hi>Mode, That Water in Baptiſm, he ſaith, hath no reſpect to the blood of Chriſt; that it doth concur in the Myſtery by way of efficacy and merit, he grants, but not as the thing there fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured, for that is the Spirit?</hi> This may help as to the manner of Baptiſing.</p>
               <p>I thought both <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies the latter, and ſaith the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> doth ſo alſo, as he thinks.</p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:32571:63"/>
               <p>The Queſtion is new to me, I ſhall hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly propound my thoughts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If cleanſing of the Soul from Sin be the thing Baptiſm holds out, then, what doth primacily, properly, and effectually cleanſe, is there ſignifyed, <hi>but the Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent is true:</hi> Cleanſing is as much given to the Blood of Chriſt, as to the Spirit. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.14.22. <hi>Almoſt all things were purged by Blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2ly, We read three times, <hi>Mark</hi> 1.4. <hi>Luke</hi> 3.3. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. that Remiſſion of Sins is ſignifyed and Sealed in Baptiſm; but how can this be, if there is no reſpect to his Blood in Baptiſm? <hi>Without Blood there is no Remiſſion, Heb.</hi> 9.22. Why is it called <hi>Baptiſm for remiſſion of ſins?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3ly, Why are we ſaid in Baptiſm to have <hi>Communion</hi> with Chriſt in his Death, and buryed with him in Baptiſm? <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3. It ſhould rather be ſaid <hi>buryed with the Spirit,</hi> if the Spirit only be ſignifyed. Doth not the Death of Chriſt compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend in it, the effuſion of his Blood?</p>
               <p n="4">4ly, It is certain, that in the <hi>Types</hi> of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> by Water the blood of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:32571:64"/>Chriſt was ſignifyed. <hi>Numb.</hi> 19.9. The Water is ſaid to be a <hi>Purification for Sin.</hi> In the <hi>Hebrew</hi> it's a Sin, the word often uſed for a <hi>Sin Offering,</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> render it, <hi>It is an Expiation.</hi> Have not that Fountain, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.1. ſet open a reſpect to the blood of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus? all the <hi>Interpreters</hi> I ſee, reſpect both his Blood and Spirit: Why not then ſo in Baptiſm.</p>
               <p n="5">5ly, As we are filthy, are we not as guilty? Is there nothing in the Ordinance to reſpect our guilt? then it were ſad, yea, guilt being upon us, can God give out the bleſſing of Regeneration to us, till in order his juſtice be firſt ſatisfied? though Regeneration and Pardon are <hi>ſimul tempore?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To ſay it concurrs by way of <hi>efficacy</hi> and <hi>merit,</hi> ſo it doth in any Ordinance to make it effectual. But Remiſſion of Sins being in a ſpecial manner ſealed up in this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which is only by Chriſts Blood, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks the Element ſhould have a reſpect to his Blood.</p>
               <p>The utter Abolition of Sin, both guilt and power is given to the Blood of Chriſt alone: but taking away guilt, is not given to the Spirit.</p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:32571:64"/>
               <p n="6">6ly, Out of the ſide of our Bleſſed Lord when he was pierced, came Blood and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.34. There is our Pardon, and Sanctification: If both theſe be ſignified in our Baptiſm, why is not that Blood and Water of his ſignifyed in this Water in Baptiſm?</p>
               <p>Hence <hi>Alcinus</hi>'s Baptiſm was ſignified in the paſſion of Chriſt, by the Water and Blood which came from his ſide; Several Verſes he hath upon it. [<hi>Cent.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 112.]</p>
               <p>In That Tract which go under <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Name. <hi>Baptizabantur in nube, &amp; mari Hebraei, &amp; jam Spiritu ſancto &amp; ſanguine Chriſti, mundatur a peccatis populus Dei. [De Reſur. Chri.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaking of Baptiſm— <hi>Ideoq<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> legiſti, quod tres Teſtes in Baptiſmate u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſunt, aqua, ſanguis; &amp; ſpiritusqui ſi unum horum detrahas, non ſtat Baptiſmatis Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum: quid enim eſt aqua ſine cruce Chriſti? [Deris qui c.</hi> 4.]</p>
               <p>Hence <hi>Luther, Baptizari nihil aliud eſt quum reſeo illo, &amp; precioſo ſanguine Chriſti, lanari, &amp; mundari.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Res ſignificata in Baptiſmo eſt ſanguis Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti.</hi> Walaeu. <hi>to.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 84. I could produce more Authors.</p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:32571:65"/>
               <p>The Application of the Blood of Chriſt, and the renewing of the Spirit, without both which our State cannot be happy, I think may both be ſignified, and theſe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Dipping, or powering of Water: <hi>The ſprinkling of the Blood of Jeſus</hi> [ſet out of old by the Ceremonial ſprinkling] is a famous Sentence in the Goſpel. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.24. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. ſo the <hi>powering out of the Spirit, Tit.</hi> 3.5, 6. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.15. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28, 29. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.23.</p>
               <p>The Aboliſhing of Sin, is the end of all; [Lord what a do is here before we can be delivered from the miſery we have brought ourſelves into! what an Evil is Sin!] now this is not ſet down one way, but ſeveral waies in Scripture, ſometimes by mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or the Death of Sin. Dipping ſets out that, <hi>Buried with Chriſt,</hi> ſometimes by clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and by purging. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.5. But the grave do not repreſent that, we do not uſe to purge, and cleanſe, by Burying, but this we do by powring Water upon our Hands, upon Rooms, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we can cleanſe that way, purge me with <hi>Hyſſop. Pſal.</hi> 51.7. How was that? <hi>Levit.</hi> 14.6, 7. <hi>Numb.</hi> 19.18. not by Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</p>
               <p>Whither then you Dip, or pour Water.
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:32571:65"/>Here is, 1. The ſame Sign, or Element. 2ly, Here is the ſame thing ſignified, the Spirit, and Blood of Chriſt. 3ly. The ſame end aimed at, the taking away, or purge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Sin; nor did I ever contend with any Man about Dipping, but to deny all Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, unleſs by Dipping, and ſo ſet up Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſing, and to adminiſter Baptiſm only to <hi>Adult</hi> perſons, excluding all the Children of Believing Parents; This I could never yield to.</p>
               <p>To conclude, though I was moved to publiſh my Notes by ſome Friends, yet had I not received this Challenge, (for ſo I may call it) by this Letter, I think I ſhould never have done it, becauſe I knew Men far more able than my ſelf, had done more ſervice, than I could do in the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie.</p>
               <p>I wiſh the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> before they had Condemned, and wrote againſt <hi>Infant-bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> had well ſtudyed, and well improved their Parental, and <hi>Infant-baptiſmal Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> followed God cloſe for the benefits, and waited, though they found temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and did not meet with all they would, and reproved others for neglecting, and vigorouſly ſtirred up people to the ſerious improvement of them; Then had they
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:32571:66"/>done good ſervice to Chriſt and his Church: Whereas by the courſe they have taken, they have increaſed our Diviſions, (a thing deeply to be lamented) which I ſhall never live to ſee healed.</p>
               <p>I ſhall only deſire the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> to give me anſwer to theſe two Queſtions, clearly from <hi>Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. 1. <hi>Since God was ſo Gracious to make a Covenant with</hi> Abraham <hi>and his</hi> Seed, <hi>and it did then conſiſt with his Wiſdom, to Conſtitute his Church of Parents and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, while the Parents did believe in the</hi> Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah to come, <hi>why may it not conſiſt with his Grace to continue that Covenant, and with his Wiſdom, still to Conſtitute his Goſpel-Church of Parents and Children, the</hi> Jews <hi>now believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Chriſt come?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If God hath plainly declared his pleaſure to the contrary, tell us where, and we are ſatisfied: but you muſt produce other Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures then you have done yet.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>If God hath repealed his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, with the Believing</hi> Jews Seed, <hi>turned their Children out of the Church, and deny them Baptiſm, though the</hi> Jews <hi>truly Believe
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:32571:66"/>in Chriſt come, what hath God left in the room of theſe, that carry any ſhew of his Bleſſing, or good Will towards their Children, during their Infant State?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to their Internall and Eternal State, the Infants were in as good a State then, as now? Chriſt is Yeſterday, to Day, and the ſame for ever, the Lamb ſlain for the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the World. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 13.8. But as to their viſible State, how come they to be in the ſame condition, that we <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and our Children were in. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt came, and we believed in him?</p>
               <p>I ſtate the Queſtion, concerning the <hi>Jews</hi> Believing in Chriſt come. As for the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Gentiles,</hi> I ſhall let them alone, till I ſee how you prove the caſting out of the Seed of the <hi>Believing Jews.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
